<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ldswebml type="broadcast" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01" order="100.testPD00046139.000" status="publish">
    <search-meta>
        <title>2018 Devotionals</title>
        <uri-title translate="no"/>
        <source translate="no">testPD00000139_000_000</source>
        <item-number>testPD00046139</item-number>
        <publication-type translate="no">broadcast</publication-type>
        <publication-date value="2018-01-01" year="2018" month="08">2013</publication-date>
        <web-publish-date translate="no">2018-06-10T09:58:47.915129-06:00</web-publish-date>
        <collections>
            <collection>global-search</collection>
            <collection>gospel-library</collection>
        </collections>
    </search-meta>
    <div class="bodyMatter">
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00045368.001" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00045368_000_001.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>What Is Truth?</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">what-is-truth</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00045368_000_001</source>
                <item-number>testPD00045368</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>Truth</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-03-06T13:24:17.23394-07:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author uri="/church/leader/dieter-f-uchtdorf">
                        <author-name>Dieter F. Uchtdorf</author-name>
                        <author-title> Of the First Presidency </author-title>
                        <author-role value="first-presidency" translate="no" living="1">First Presidency</author-role>
                        <author-rank translate="no">02</author-rank>
                        <author-seniority translate="no">02</author-seniority>
                        <image type="jpg" uri="dieter-f-uchtdorf-10.jpg" translate="no"/>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.head1">
                <h1>What Is Truth?</h1>
                <div class="authorName">Dieter F. Uchtdorf</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p4">My beloved brothers and sisters, my dear young friends, I am grateful for the privilege to be with you today. It always lifts my spirits to be surrounded by the young adults of the Church, and you inspire me to declare, “Let Zion in her beauty rise.” As you are living all around the world, you represent in a beautiful way the future and strength of the Church. Because of your righteous desires and your commitment to follow the Savior, the future of this Church looks bright.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p5">I bring you the love and blessing of President Thomas S. Monson. The First Presidency prays for you often. We always ask the Lord to bless, keep, and guide you.</block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t1">
                    <div class="title"> The Blind Men and the Elephant </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p7">Well over one hundred years ago, an American poet put to rhyme an ancient parable. The first verse of the poem speaks about:</block>
                    <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.f1">
                        <div class="stanza">
                            <div class="line">Six men of Indostan</div>
                            <div class="line">To learning much inclined,</div>
                            <div class="line">Who went to see the Elephant</div>
                            <div class="line">(Though all of them were blind),</div>
                            <div class="line">That each by observation</div>
                            <div class="line">Might satisfy his mind.</div>
                        </div>
                    </block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p14">In the poem each of the six travelers takes hold of a different part of the elephant and then describes to the others what he has discovered.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p15">One of the men finds the elephant’s leg and describes it as being round and rough like a tree. Another feels the tusk and describes the elephant as a spear. A third grabs the tail and insists that an elephant is like a rope. A fourth discovers the trunk and insists that the elephant is like a large snake.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p16">Each is describing truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p17">And because his truth comes from personal experience, each insists that he knows what he knows.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p18">The poem concludes:</block>
                    <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.f2">
                        <div class="stanza">
                            <div class="line">And so these men of Indostan</div>
                            <div class="line">Disputed loud and long,</div>
                            <div class="line">Each in his own opinion</div>
                            <div class="line">Exceeding stiff and strong,</div>
                            <div class="line">Though each was partly in the right,</div>
                            <div class="line">And all were in the wrong!<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="1"><a href="#1">1</a></sup></div>
                        </div>
                    </block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p25">We look at this story from a distance and smile. After all, we know what an elephant looks like. We have read about them and watched them on film, and many of us have even seen one with our own eyes. We believe we know the truth of what an elephant is. That someone could make a judgment based on one aspect of truth and apply it to the whole seems absurd or even unbelievable. On the other hand, can’t we recognize ourselves in these six blind men? Have we ever been guilty of the same pattern of thought?</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p26">I suppose the reason this story has remained so popular in so many cultures and over so many years is because of its universal application. The Apostle Paul said that in this world the light is dim and we see only part of the truth as though we are looking “through a glass, darkly.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="2"><a href="#2">2</a></sup> And yet it seems to be part of our nature as human beings to make assumptions about people, politics, and piety based on our incomplete and often misleading experience.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p27">I am reminded of a story about a couple who had been married for 60 years. They had rarely argued during that time, and their days together passed in happiness and contentment. They shared everything and had no secrets between them—except one. The wife had a box that she kept at the top of a sideboard, and she told her husband when they were married that he should never look inside.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p28">As the decades passed, the moment came that her husband took the box down and asked if he could finally know what it contained. The wife consented, and he opened it to discover two doilies and $25,000. When he asked his wife what this meant, she responded, “When we were married, my mother told me that whenever I was angry with you or whenever you said or did something I didn’t like, I should knit a small doily and then talk things through with you.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p29">The husband was moved to tears by this sweet story. He marveled that during 60 years of marriage he had only disturbed his wife enough for her to knit two doilies. Feeling extremely good about himself, he took his wife’s hand and said, “That explains the doilies, but what about the $25,000?”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p30">His wife smiled sweetly and said, “That’s the money I got from selling all the doilies I’ve knitted over the years.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p31">Not only does this story teach an interesting way to deal with disagreements in marriage, but it also illustrates the folly of jumping to conclusions based on limited information.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p32">So often the “truths” we tell ourselves are merely fragments of the truth, and sometimes they’re not really the truth at all.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p33">Today I would like to speak of truth. As I do, I invite you to ponder a few important questions.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p34">The first question is <i>“What is truth?”</i></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p35">The second, <i>“Is it really possible to know the truth?”</i></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p36">And third, <i>“How should we react to things that contradict truths which we have learned previously?”</i></block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t2">
                    <div class="title"> What Is Truth? </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p38">What is truth? During the closing hours of His life, the Savior was brought before Pontius Pilate. The elders of the Jews had accused Jesus of sedition and treason against Rome and insisted that He be put to death.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p39">When Pilate came face to face with the Man of Galilee, he asked, “Are you a king?”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p40">Jesus replied, “For this cause came I into the world, that I should bear witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="3"><a href="#3">3</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p41">I don’t know what kind of man Pilate was, nor do I know what he was thinking. However, I suspect that he was well educated and had seen much of the known world.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p42">I sense a certain weary cynicism in Pilate’s reply. I hear in his words the voice of a man who may once have been an idealist but now—after a great deal of life experience—seems a little hardened, even tired.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p43">I don’t believe Pilate was encouraging a dialogue when he responded with three simple words: “What is truth?”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="4"><a href="#4">4</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p44">To amplify, I wonder if what he really was asking was “How can anyone possibly know the truth?”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p45">And that is a question for all time and for all people.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t3">
                    <div class="title"> Can Anyone Know the Truth? </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p47">Now, can anyone know the truth? Some of the greatest minds that have ever lived on this earth have attempted to answer that question. The elusive nature of truth has been a favorite theme of history’s great poets and storytellers. Shakespeare seemed especially intrigued with it. The next time you read one of Shakespeare’s tragedies, notice how often the plot turns on a misunderstanding of an important truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p48">Now, never in the history of the world have we had easier access to more information—some of it true, some of it false, and much of it partially true.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p49">Consequently, never in the history of the world has it been more important to learn how to correctly discern between truth and error.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p50">Part of our problem in the quest for truth is that human wisdom has disappointed us so often. We have so many examples of things that mankind once “knew” were true but have since been proven false.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p51">For example, in spite of one-time overwhelming consensus, the earth isn’t flat. The stars don’t revolve around the earth. Eating a tomato will not cause instant death. And, of course, man actually can fly—even break the sound barrier.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p52">The scriptures are filled with stories of men and women who misinterpreted “truth.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p53">In the Old Testament, Balaam could not resist the “wages of unrighteousness”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="5"><a href="#5">5</a></sup><a href="/scriptures/bible/bible" class="scriptureRef"/> offered him by the Moabites. So he convinced himself to believe a new truth and helped the Moabites get the Israelites to curse themselves through immorality and disobedience.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="6"><a href="#6">6</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p54">The apostate Korihor, after leading many away from the truth, confessed that the devil had deceived him to the point where he actually believed that what he was saying was the truth.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="7"><a href="#7">7</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p55">In the Book of Mormon, both the Nephites as well as the Lamanites created their own “truths” about each other. The Nephites’ “truth” about the Lamanites was that they “were a wild, and ferocious, and a blood-thirsty people,”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="8"><a href="#8">8</a></sup> never able to accept the gospel. The Lamanites’ “truth” about the Nephites was that Nephi had stolen his brother’s birthright and that Nephi’s descendants were liars who continued to rob the Lamanites of what was rightfully theirs.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="9"><a href="#9">9</a></sup> These “truths” fed their hatred for one another until it finally consumed them all.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p56">Needless to say, there are many examples in the Book of Mormon that contradict both of these stereotypes. Nevertheless, the Nephites and Lamanites believed these “truths” that shaped the destiny of this once-mighty and beautiful people.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t4">
                    <div class="title"> Human Nature and Truth </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p58">In some way we are all susceptible to such strange thinking.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p59">The “truths” we cling to shape the quality of our societies as well as our individual characters. All too often these “truths” are based on incomplete and inaccurate evidence, and at times they serve very selfish motives.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p60">Part of the reason for poor judgment comes from the tendency of mankind to blur the line between belief and truth. We too often confuse belief with truth, thinking that because something makes sense or is convenient, it must be true. Conversely, we sometimes don’t believe truth or reject it—because it would require us to change or admit that we were wrong. Often, truth is rejected because it doesn’t appear to be consistent with previous experiences.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p61">When the opinions or “truths” of others contradict our own, instead of considering the possibility that there could be information that might be helpful and augment or complement what we know, we often jump to conclusions or make assumptions that the other person is misinformed, mentally challenged, or even intentionally trying to deceive.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p62">Unfortunately, this tendency can spread to all areas of our lives—from sports to family relationships and from religion to politics.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t5">
                    <div class="title"> Ignaz Semmelweis </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p64">A tragic example of this tendency is the story of Ignaz Semmelweis, a Hungarian physician who practiced medicine during the mid-19th century. Early in his career, Dr. Semmelweis learned that 10 percent of the women who came to his clinic died of childbed fever, while the death rate at a nearby clinic was less than 4 percent. He was determined to find out why.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p65">After investigating the two clinics, Dr. Semmelweis concluded that the only significant difference was that his was a teaching clinic where corpses were examined. He observed doctors who went directly from performing autopsies to delivering babies. He concluded that somehow the corpses had contaminated their hands and caused the deadly fevers.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p66">When he began to recommend that doctors scrub their hands with a chlorinated lime solution, he was met with indifference and even scorn. His conclusions contradicted the “truths” of other doctors. Some of his colleagues even believed that it was absurd to think that a doctor’s hand could be impure or cause sickness.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p67">But Semmelweis insisted, and he made it a policy for doctors in his clinic to wash their hands before delivering babies. As a consequence, the death rate promptly dropped by 90 percent. Semmelweis felt vindicated and was certain that this practice would now be adopted throughout the medical community. But he was wrong. Even his dramatic results were not enough to change the minds of many doctors of the day.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t6">
                    <div class="title"> Is It Possible to Know the Truth? </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p69">The thing about truth is that it exists beyond belief. It is true even if nobody believes it.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p70">We can say west is north and north is west all day long and even believe it with all our heart, but if, for example, we want to fly from Quito, Ecuador, to New York City in the United States, there is only one direction that will lead us there, and that is north—west just won’t do.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p71">Of course, this is just a simple aviation analogy. However, there is indeed such a thing as absolute truth—unassailable, unchangeable truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p72">This truth is different from belief. It is different from hope. Absolute truth is not dependent upon public opinion or popularity. Polls cannot sway it. Not even the inexhaustible authority of celebrity endorsement can change it.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p73">So how can we find truth?</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p74">I believe that our Father in Heaven is pleased with His children when they use their talents and mental faculties to earnestly discover truth. Over the centuries many wise men and women—through logic, reason, scientific inquiry, and, yes, through inspiration—have discovered truth. These discoveries have enriched mankind, improved our lives, and inspired joy, wonder, and awe.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p75">Even so, the things we once thought we knew are continually being enhanced, modified, or even contradicted by enterprising scholars who seek to understand truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p76">As we all know, it is difficult enough to sort out the truth from our own experiences. To make matters worse, we have an adversary, “the devil, [who] as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="10"><a href="#10">10</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p77">Satan is the great deceiver, “the accuser of [the] brethren,”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="11"><a href="#11">11</a></sup> the father of all lies,<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="12"><a href="#12">12</a></sup> who continually seeks to deceive that he might overthrow us.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="13"><a href="#13">13</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p78">The adversary has many cunning strategies for keeping mortals from the truth. He offers the belief that truth is relative; appealing to our sense of tolerance and fairness, he keeps the real truth hidden by claiming that one person’s “truth” is as valid as any other.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p79">Some he entices to believe that there is an absolute truth out there somewhere but that it is impossible for anyone to know it.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p80">For those who already embrace the truth, his primary strategy is to spread the seeds of doubt. For example, he has caused many members of the Church to stumble when they discover information about the Church that seems to contradict what they had learned previously.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p81">If you experience such a moment, remember that in this age of information there are many who create doubt about anything and everything, at any time and every place.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p82">You will find even those who still claim that they have evidence that the earth is flat, that the moon is a hologram, and that certain movie stars are really aliens from another planet. And it is always good to keep in mind, just because something is printed on paper, appears on the Internet, is frequently repeated, or has a powerful group of followers doesn’t make it true.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p83">Sometimes untrue claims or information are presented in such a way that they appear quite credible. However, when you are confronted with information that is in conflict with the revealed word of God, remember that the blind men in the parable of the elephant would never be able to accurately describe the full truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p84">We simply don’t know all things—we can’t see everything. What may seem contradictory now may be perfectly understandable as we search for and receive more trustworthy information. Because we see through a glass darkly, we have to trust the Lord, who sees all things clearly.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p85">Yes, our world is full of confusion. But eventually all of our questions will be answered. All of our doubts will be replaced by certainty. And that is because there is one source of truth that is complete, correct, and incorruptible. That source is our infinitely wise and all-knowing Heavenly Father. He knows truth as it was, as it is, and as it yet will be.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="14"><a href="#14">14</a></sup> “He comprehendeth all things, … and he is above all things, … and all things are by him, and of him.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="15"><a href="#15">15</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p86">Our loving Heavenly Father offers His truth to us, His mortal children.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p87">Now, what is this truth?</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p88">It is His gospel. It is the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus Christ is “the way, the truth, and the life.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="16"><a href="#16">16</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p89">If we will only have enough courage and faith to walk in His path, it will lead us to peace of heart and mind, to lasting meaning in life, to happiness in this world, and to joy in the world to come. The Savior is “not far from every one of us.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="17"><a href="#17">17</a></sup> We have His promise that if we seek Him diligently, we will find Him.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="18"><a href="#18">18</a></sup></block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t7">
                    <div class="title"> Our Obligation to Seek for Truth </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p91">But how can we know that this “truth” is different from any other? How can we trust this “truth”?</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p92">The invitation to trust the Lord does not relieve us from the responsibility to know for ourselves. This is more than an opportunity; it is an obligation—and it is one of the reasons we were sent to this earth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p93">Latter-day Saints are not asked to blindly accept everything they hear. We are encouraged to think and discover truth for ourselves. We are expected to ponder, to search, to evaluate, and thereby to come to a personal knowledge of the truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p94">Brigham Young said: “I am … afraid that this people have so much confidence in their leaders that they will not inquire for themselves of God whether they are led by him. I am fearful they settle down in a state of blind self-security. … Let every man and woman know, by the whispering of the Spirit of God to themselves, whether their leaders are walking in the path the Lord dictates.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="19"><a href="#19">19</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p95">We seek for truth wherever we may find it. The Prophet Joseph Smith taught that “Mormonism is truth. … The first and fundamental principle of our holy religion is, that we believe that we have a right to embrace all, and every item of truth, without limitation or … being … prohibited by the creeds or superstitious notions of men.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="20"><a href="#20">20</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p96">Yes, we do have the fulness of the everlasting gospel, but that does not mean that we know everything. In fact, one principle of the restored gospel is our belief that God “will yet reveal many great and important things.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="21"><a href="#21">21</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p97">The Restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ came about because of a young man with a humble heart and a keen mind seeking for truth. Joseph studied and then acted accordingly. He discovered that if a man lacks wisdom, he can ask of God and the truth really will be given unto him.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="22"><a href="#22">22</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p98">The great miracle of the Restoration was not just that it corrected false ideas and corrupt doctrines—though it certainly did that—but that it flung open the curtains of heaven and initiated a steady downpour of new light and knowledge that has continued to this day.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p99">So we continually seek truth from all good books and other wholesome sources. “If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="23"><a href="#23">23</a></sup> In this manner we can resist the deceit of the evil one. In this manner we learn the truth “precept upon precept; line upon line.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="24"><a href="#24">24</a></sup> And we will learn that intelligence cleaves unto intelligence, and wisdom receives wisdom, and truth embraces truth.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="25"><a href="#25">25</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p100">My young friends, as you accept the responsibility to seek after truth with an open mind and a humble heart, you will become more tolerant of others, more open to listen, more prepared to understand, more inclined to build up instead of tearing down, and more willing to go where the Lord wants you to go.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.t8">
                    <div class="title"> The Holy Ghost—Our Guide to All Truth </div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p102">Just think about it. You actually have a powerful companion and trustworthy guide in this ongoing search for truth. Who is it? It is the Holy Ghost. Our Heavenly Father knew how difficult it would be for us to sift through all the competing noise and discover truth during our mortality. He knew we would see only a portion of the truth, and He knew that Satan would try to deceive us. So He gave us the heavenly gift of the Holy Ghost to illuminate our minds, teach us, and testify to us of the truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p103">The Holy Ghost is a revelator. He is the Comforter, who teaches us “the truth of all things; … [who] knoweth all things, and hath all power according to wisdom, mercy, truth, justice, and judgment.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="26"><a href="#26">26</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p104">The Holy Ghost is a certain and safe guide to assist all mortals who seek God as they navigate the often troubling waters of confusion and contradiction.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p105">The <i>Witness</i> of truth from the Holy Ghost is available to all, everywhere, all around the globe. All who seek to know the truth, who study it out in their minds,<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="27"><a href="#27">27</a></sup> and who “ask with a sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, [will know] the truth … by the power of the Holy Ghost.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="28"><a href="#28">28</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p106">And there is the additional, unspeakable <i>Gift</i> of the Holy Ghost available to all who qualify themselves through baptism and by living worthy of His constant companionship.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p107">Yes, your loving Father in Heaven would never leave you alone in this mortality to wander in the dark. You need not be deceived. You can overcome the darkness of this world and discover divine truth.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p108">Some, however, do not seek for truth so much as they strive for contention. They do not sincerely seek to learn; rather, they desire to dispute, to show off their supposed learning and thus cause contention. They ignore or reject the counsel of the Apostle Paul to Timothy: “Foolish and unlearned questions avoid, knowing that they do [generate contention].”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="29"><a href="#29">29</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p109">As disciples of Jesus Christ, we know that such contention is completely inconsistent with the Spirit upon whom we depend in our search for truth. As the Savior warned the Nephites, “For verily … I say unto you, he that hath the spirit of contention is not of me, but is of the devil, who is the father of contention.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="30"><a href="#30">30</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p110">If you follow the Spirit, your personal search for the truth inevitably leads you to the Lord and Savior, even Jesus Christ, for He is “the way, the truth, and the life.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="31"><a href="#31">31</a></sup> This may not be the most convenient way; it will probably also be the road less traveled, and it will be the path with mountains to climb, swift rivers to cross, but it will be His way—the Savior’s redeeming way.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p111">I add my witness as an Apostle of the Lord, that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the living God. I know this with all my heart and mind. I know this by the witness and power of the Holy Ghost.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p112">I ask you to spare no efforts in your search to know this truth for yourself—because this truth will make you free.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="32"><a href="#32">32</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p113">My dear young friends, you are the hope of Israel. We love you. The Lord knows you; He loves you. The Lord has great confidence in you. He knows your successes, and He is mindful of your challenges and questions in life.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p114">It is my prayer that you will seek the truth earnestly and unceasingly, that you will yearn to drink from the fount of all truth, whose waters are pure and sweet, “a well of water springing up into everlasting life.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="33"><a href="#33">33</a></sup></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p115">I bless you with confidence in the Lord and a deep-rooted desire to rightfully discern truth from error—now and throughout your life. This is my prayer and my blessing, in the sacred name of Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
                </block>
            </div>
            <div class="notes">
                <div class="title">Notes</div>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn1" ref="1">
                    <p><span class="label">1.</span> John Godfrey Saxe, <i>The Poems of John Godfrey Saxe</i> (1873), 135–36, books.google.com.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn2" ref="2">
                    <p><span class="label">2.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-cor/13.12" class="scriptureRef">1 </a>
                        <a href="/scriptures/bible/bible" class="scriptureRef"/>
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-cor/13.12" class="scriptureRef">Corinthians 13:12</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn3" ref="3">
                    <p><span class="label">3.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/18.37" class="scriptureRef">John 18:37</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn4" ref="4">
                    <p><span class="label">4.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/18.33-38" class="scriptureRef">John 18:33–38</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn5" ref="5">
                    <p><span class="label">5.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/2-pet/2.15" class="scriptureRef">2 Peter 2:15</a>. </p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn6" ref="6">
                    <p><span class="label">6.</span> For Balaam’s story, see <a href="/scriptures/ot/num/22?span=22-24" class="scriptureRef">Numbers 22–24</a>; see also <a href="/scriptures/ot/num/31.16" class="scriptureRef">Numbers 31:16</a>; <a href="/scriptures/nt/rev/2.14" class="scriptureRef">Revelation 2:14</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn7" ref="7">
                    <p><span class="label">7.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/30.52-53" class="scriptureRef">Alma 30:</a><a href="/scriptures/bible/bible" class="scriptureRef"/><a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/30.52,53" class="scriptureRef">52–53</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn8" ref="8">
                    <p><span class="label">8.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/10.12" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 10:12</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn9" ref="9">
                    <p><span class="label">9.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/10.12" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 10:12</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/20.13" class="scriptureRef">Alma 20:13</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn10" ref="10">
                    <p><span class="label">10.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-pet/5.8" class="scriptureRef">1 Peter 5:8</a>.<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/10.12" class="scriptureRef"/></p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn11" ref="11">
                    <p><span class="label">11.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/rev/12.10" class="scriptureRef">Revelation 12:10</a>.<a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/20.13" class="scriptureRef"/></p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn12" ref="12">
                    <p><span class="label">12.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/8.44" class="scriptureRef">John 8:44</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn13" ref="13">
                    <p><span class="label">13.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/50.3" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine </a><a href="/scriptures/bible/bible" class="scriptureRef"/><a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/50.3" class="scriptureRef">and Covenants 50:3</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn14" ref="14">
                    <p><span class="label">14.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/93.24" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 93:24</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn15" ref="15">
                    <p><span class="label">15.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/88.41" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 88:41</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn16" ref="16">
                    <p><span class="label">16.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/14.6" class="scriptureRef">John 14:6</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn17" ref="17">
                    <p><span class="label">17.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/acts/17.27" class="scriptureRef">Acts 17:27</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn18" ref="18">
                    <p><span class="label">18.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/ot/deut/4.29" class="scriptureRef">Deuteronomy 4:29</a>; <a href="/scriptures/ot/prov/8.17" class="scriptureRef">Proverbs 8:17</a>; <a href="/scriptures/nt/acts/17.27" class="scriptureRef">Acts 17:27</a>; <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/88.63" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 88:63</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn19" ref="19">
                    <p><span class="label">19.</span> 
                        <i>Discourses of Brigham Young,</i> sel. John A. Widtsoe (1941), 135.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn20" ref="20">
                    <p><span class="label">20.</span> 
                        <i>Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Smith</i> (2007), 264.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn21" ref="21">
                    <p><span class="label">21.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/pgp/a-of-f/1.9" class="scriptureRef">Articles of Faith 1:9</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn22" ref="22">
                    <p><span class="label">22.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/nt/james/1.5" class="scriptureRef">James 1:5</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn23" ref="23">
                    <p><span class="label">23.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/pgp/a-of-f/1.13" class="scriptureRef">Articles of Faith 1:13</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn24" ref="24">
                    <p><span class="label">24.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/ot/isa/28.10" class="scriptureRef">Isaiah 28:10</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn25" ref="25">
                    <p><span class="label">25.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/88.40" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 88:40</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn26" ref="26">
                    <p><span class="label">26.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/pgp/moses/6.61" class="scriptureRef">Moses 6:61</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn27" ref="27">
                    <p><span class="label">27.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/9.8" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 9:8</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn28" ref="28">
                    <p><span class="label">28.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/bofm/moro/10.4" class="scriptureRef">Moroni 10:4</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn29" ref="29">
                    <p><span class="label">29.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/2-tim/2.23" class="scriptureRef">2 Timothy 2:23</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn30" ref="30">
                    <p><span class="label">30.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/11.29" class="scriptureRef">3 Nephi 11:29</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn31" ref="31">
                    <p><span class="label">31.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/14.6" class="scriptureRef">John 14:6</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn32" ref="32">
                    <p><span class="label">32.</span>  See <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/8.32" class="scriptureRef">John 8:32</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.fn33" ref="33">
                    <p><span class="label">33.</span> 
                        <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/4.14" class="scriptureRef">John 4:14</a>.</p>
                </block>
            </div>
            <div class="resources">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/what-is-truth.p150">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 8/12. <i>What Is Truth?</i> testPD00045368 000</block>
                </block>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00045417.001" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00045417_000_001.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>That We Might “Not … Shrink” (D&amp;C 19:18)</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00045417_000_001</source>
                <item-number>testPD00045417</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>discipleship</subject>
                    <subject>faith</subject>
                    <subject>courage</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-03-21T14:02:00.228-06:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author uri="/church/leader/david-a-bednar">
                        <author-name>David A. Bednar</author-name>
                        <author-title>Of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles</author-title>
                        <author-role value="twelve" translate="no" living="1">Twelve</author-role>
                        <author-rank translate="no">03</author-rank>
                        <author-seniority translate="no">09</author-seniority>
                        <image type="jpg" uri="david-a-bednar-10.jpg" translate="no"/>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.head1">
                <h1>That We Might “Not … Shrink” (D&amp;C 19:18)</h1>
                <div class="authorName">David A. Bednar</div>
                <div class="event">CES Devotional for Young Adults • March 3, 2013 • University of Texas Arlington</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p5">I am grateful to participate in this devotional with young people of the Church from all over the world. I love you and appreciate this opportunity to worship together.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p6">Susan has spoken and testified of important principles, and each of us will be blessed and strengthened as we apply consistently her teachings in our daily lives. Susan is a righteous woman, an elect lady, and the love of my life.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p7">I have pondered and earnestly petitioned our Heavenly Father to know how I might best be able to serve you tonight. I pray the power of the Holy Ghost will be with each of us—that we may think what we need to think, feel what we need to feel, and learn what we need to learn so we can do what we know we should do and ultimately become what the Lord yearns for us to become.</block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t1">
                    <div class="title">A Devoted Disciple and an Example of Not Shrinking</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p9">Elder Neal A. Maxwell was a beloved disciple of the Lord Jesus Christ. He served as a member of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles for 23 years, from 1981 to 2004. The spiritual power of his teachings and his example of faithful discipleship blessed and continue to bless in marvelous ways the members of the Savior’s restored Church and the people of the world.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p10">In October of 1997, Sister Bednar and I hosted Elder and Sister Maxwell at Brigham Young University–Idaho. Elder Maxwell was to speak to the students, staff, and faculty in a devotional assembly. Everyone on the campus eagerly anticipated his visit to the university and earnestly prepared to receive his message.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p11">Earlier in that same year, Elder Maxwell underwent 46 days and nights of debilitating chemotherapy for leukemia. Shortly after completing his treatments and being released from the hospital, he spoke briefly in the April general conference of the Church. His rehabilitation and continued therapy progressed positively through the spring and summer months, but Elder Maxwell’s physical strength and stamina were nonetheless limited when he traveled to Rexburg. After greeting Elder and Sister Maxwell at the airport, Susan and I drove them to our home for rest and a light lunch before the devotional.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p12">During the course of our conversations that day, I asked Elder Maxwell what lessons he had learned through his illness. I will remember always the precise and penetrating answer he gave. “Dave,” he said, “I have learned that not shrinking is more important than surviving.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p13">His response to my inquiry was a principle with which he had gained extensive personal experience during his chemotherapy. As Elder Maxwell and his wife were driving to the hospital in January of 1997, on the day he was scheduled to begin his first round of treatment, they pulled into the parking lot and paused for a private moment together. Elder Maxwell “breathed a deep sigh and looked at [his wife]. He reached for her hand and said … , ‘I just don’t want to shrink’” (Bruce C. Hafen, <i>A Disciple’s Life: The Biography of Neal A. Maxwell</i> [2002], 16).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p14">In his October 1997 general conference message, entitled “Apply the Atoning Blood of Christ,” Elder Maxwell taught with great authenticity: “As we confront our own … trials and tribulations, we too can plead with the Father, just as Jesus did, that we ‘might not … shrink’—meaning to retreat or to recoil (<a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/19.18" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 19:18</a>). Not shrinking is much more important than surviving! Moreover, partaking of a bitter cup without becoming bitter is likewise part of the emulation of Jesus” (<i>Ensign,</i> Nov. 1997, 22).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p15">Elder Maxwell’s answer to my question caused me to reflect on the teachings of Elder Orson F. Whitney, who also served as a member of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles: “No pain that we suffer, no trial that we experience is wasted. It ministers to our education, to the development of such qualities as patience, faith, fortitude and humility. All that we suffer and all that we endure, especially when we endure patiently, builds up our characters, purifies our hearts, expands our souls, and makes us more tender and charitable, more worthy to be called the children of God … and it is through sorrow and suffering, toil and tribulation, that we gain the education that we come here to acquire” (quoted in Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Faith Precedes the Miracle</i> [1972], 98).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p16">And these scriptures concerning the Savior’s suffering as He offered the infinite and eternal atoning sacrifice became even more poignant and meaningful to me:</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p17">“Therefore I command you to repent—repent, lest I smite you by the rod of my mouth, and by my wrath, and by my anger, and your sufferings be sore—how sore you know not, how exquisite you know not, yea, how hard to bear you know not.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p18">“For behold, I, God, have suffered these things for all, that they might not suffer if they would repent;</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p19">“But if they would not repent they must suffer even as I;</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p20">“Which suffering caused myself, even God, the greatest of all, to tremble because of pain, and to bleed at every pore, and to suffer both body and spirit—and would that I might not drink the bitter cup, and shrink—</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p21">“Nevertheless, glory be to the Father, and I partook and finished my preparations unto the children of men” (<a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/19.16-19" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C</a><a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/19.15-19" class="scriptureRef">19:15–19).</a></block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p22">The Savior did not shrink in Gethsemane or on Golgotha.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p23">Elder Maxwell also did not shrink. This mighty Apostle pressed forward steadfastly and was blessed with additional time in mortality to love, to serve, to teach, and to testify. Those concluding years of his life were an emphatic exclamation point to his example of devoted discipleship—through both his words and his deeds.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p24">I believe most of us likely would expect a man with the spiritual capacity, experience, and stature of Elder Maxwell to face serious illness and death with an understanding of God’s plan of happiness, with assurance and grace, and with dignity. And he surely did. But my purpose today is to bear witness that such blessings are not reserved exclusively for General Authorities or for a select few members of the Church.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p25">Since my call to fill the vacancy in the Quorum of the Twelve created by the death of Elder Maxwell, my assignments and travels have enabled me to become acquainted with faithful, courageous, and valiant Latter-day Saints all over the world. I want to tell you about one young man and one young woman who have blessed my life and with whom I have learned spiritually vital lessons about not shrinking and about allowing our individual will to be “swallowed up in the will of the Father” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/15.7" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 15:7</a>).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p26">The account is true, and the characters are real. I will not, however, use the actual names of the individuals who are involved. I refer to the young man as John and the young woman as Heather. I also use with permission selected statements from their personal journals.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t2">
                    <div class="title">Not My Will but Thine Be Done</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p28">John is a worthy priesthood holder and served faithfully as a full-time missionary. After returning home from his mission, he dated and married a righteous and wonderful young woman, Heather. John was 23 and Heather was 20 on the day they were sealed together for time and for all eternity in the house of the Lord. Please keep in mind the respective ages of John and Heather as this story unfolds.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p29">Approximately three weeks after their temple marriage, John was diagnosed with bone cancer. As cancer nodules also were discovered in his lungs, the prognosis was not good.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p30">John recorded in his journal: “This was the scariest day of my life. Not only because I was told I had cancer, but also because I was newly married and somehow felt that I had failed as a husband. I was the provider and protector of our new family, and now—three weeks into that role—I felt like I had failed. I know that thought is absurd, but it is one of the crazy things I told myself in a moment of crisis.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p31">Heather noted: “This was devastating news, and I remember how greatly it changed our perspectives. I was in a hospital waiting room writing wedding thank-you notes as we anticipated the results of [John’s] tests. But after learning about [John’s] cancer, crock-pots and cookware did not seem so important anymore. This was the worst day of my life, but I remember going to bed that night with gratitude for our temple sealing. Though the doctors had given [John] only a 30 percent chance of survival, I knew that if we remained faithful I had a 100 percent chance to be with him forever.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p32">Approximately one month later John began chemotherapy. He described his experience: “The treatments caused me to be sicker than I had ever been in my life. I lost my hair, dropped 41 pounds, and my body felt like it was falling apart. The chemotherapy also affected me emotionally, mentally, and spiritually. Life was a rollercoaster during the months of chemo with highs, lows, and everything in between. But through it all, [Heather] and I maintained the faith that God would heal me. We just knew it.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p33">Heather chronicled her thoughts and feelings: “I could not stand to let [John] spend the night alone in the hospital, so I would sleep every night on the small couch in his room. We had lots of friends and family visit during the day, but the nights were the hardest. I would stare at the ceiling and wonder what Heavenly Father had planned for us. Sometimes my mind would wander into dark places, and my fear of losing [John] would almost overtake me. But I knew these thoughts were not from Heavenly Father. My prayers for comfort became more frequent, and the Lord gave me the strength to keep going.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p34">Three months later John underwent a surgical procedure to remove a large tumor in his leg. John stated: “The surgery was a huge deal for us because pathology tests were to be run on the tumor to see how much of it was viable and how much of the cancer was dead. This analysis would give us the first indication of the effectiveness of the chemotherapy and of how aggressive we would need to be with future treatments.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p35">Two days following the operation, I visited John and Heather in the hospital. We talked about the first time I met John in the mission field, about their marriage, about the cancer, and about the eternally important lessons we learn through the trials of mortality. As we concluded our time together, John asked if I would give him a priesthood blessing. I responded that I gladly would give such a blessing, but I first needed to ask some questions.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p36">I then posed questions I had not planned to ask and had never previously considered: “[John,] do you have the faith not to be healed? If it is the will of our Heavenly Father that you are transferred by death in your youth to the spirit world to continue your ministry, do you have the faith to submit to His will and not be healed?”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p37">I frankly was surprised by the questions I felt prompted to ask this particular couple. Frequently in the scriptures, the Savior or His servants exercised the spiritual gift of healing (see <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-cor/12.9" class="scriptureRef">1 Corinthians 12:9</a>;<a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/35.9" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 35:9</a>; <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/46.20" class="scriptureRef">46:20</a>) and perceived that an individual had the faith to be healed (see <a href="/scriptures/nt/acts/14.9" class="scriptureRef">Acts 14:9</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/17.8" class="scriptureRef">3 Nephi 17:8</a>; <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/46.19" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 46:19</a>). But as John and Heather and I counseled together and wrestled with these questions, we increasingly understood that if God’s will were for this good young man to be healed, then that blessing could only be received if this valiant couple first had the faith not to be healed. In other words, John and Heather needed to overcome, through the Atonement of the Lord Jesus Christ, the “natural man” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/3.19" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 3:19</a>) tendency in all of us to demand impatiently and insist incessantly on the blessings we want and believe we deserve.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p38">We recognized a principle that applies to every devoted disciple: strong faith in the Savior is submissively accepting of His will and timing in our lives—even if the outcome is not what we hoped for or wanted. Certainly, John and Heather would desire, yearn, and plead for healing with all of their might, mind, and strength. But more importantly, they would be “willing to submit to all things which the Lord seeth fit to inflict upon [them], even as a child doth submit to his father” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/3.19" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 3:19</a>). Indeed, they would be willing to “offer [their] whole souls as an offering unto him” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/omni/1.26" class="scriptureRef">Omni 1:26</a>) and humbly pray, “Father, if thou be willing, remove this cup from me: nevertheless not my will, but thine, be done” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/luke/22.42" class="scriptureRef">Luke 22:42</a>).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p39">What initially seemed to John, Heather, and me to be perplexing questions became part of a pervasive pattern of gospel paradoxes. Consider the admonition of the Savior: “He that findeth his life shall lose it: and he that loseth his life for my sake shall find it” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/matt/10.39" class="scriptureRef">Matthew 10:39</a>). He also declared, “But many that are first shall be last; and the last shall be first” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/matt/19.30" class="scriptureRef">Matthew 19:30</a>). And the Lord counseled His latter-day disciples, “By thy word many high ones shall be brought low, and by thy word many low ones shall be exalted” (<a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/112.8" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 112:8</a>). Thus, having the faith to not be healed seemed to fit appropriately into a powerful pattern of penetrating paradoxes that require us to ask, to seek, and to knock that we might receive knowledge and understanding (see <a href="/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/14.7" class="scriptureRef">3 Nephi 14:7</a>).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p40">After taking the necessary time to ponder my inquiries and to talk with his wife, John said to me: “Elder Bednar, I do not want to die. I do not want to leave [Heather]. But if the will of the Lord is to transfer me to the spirit world, then I guess I am good with that.” My heart swelled with appreciation and admiration as I witnessed this young couple confront the most demanding of all spiritual struggles—the submissive surrender of their wills to God’s will. My faith was strengthened as I witnessed this couple allowing their strong and understandable desires for healing to be “swallowed up in the will of the Father” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/15.7" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 15:7</a>).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p41">John described his reaction to our conversation and the blessing he received: “Elder Bednar shared with us the thought from Elder Maxwell that it is better to not shrink than to survive. Elder Bednar then asked us, ‘I know you have the faith to be healed, but do you have the faith not to be healed?’ This was a foreign concept to me. Essentially he was asking if I had the faith to accept God’s will if His will were that I not be healed? If the time were approaching for me to enter the spirit world through death, was I prepared to submit and accept?”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p42">John continued: “Having the faith not to be healed seemed counterintuitive; but that perspective changed the way my wife and I thought and allowed us to put our trust fully in the Father’s plan for us. We learned we needed to gain the faith that the Lord is in charge whatever the outcome may be, and He will guide us from where we are to where we need to be. As we prayed, our petitions changed from ‘Please make me whole’ to ‘Please give me the faith to accept whatever outcome Thou hast planned for me.’</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p43">“I was sure that since Elder Bednar was an Apostle, he would bless the elements of my body to realign, and I would jump out of the bed and start to dance or do something dramatic like that! But as he blessed me that day, I was amazed that the words he spoke were almost identical to those of my father, my father-in-law, and my mission president. I realized that ultimately it does not matter whose hands are on my head. God’s power does not change, and His will is made known to us individually and through His authorized servants.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p44">Heather wrote: “This day was filled with mixed emotions for me. I was convinced that Elder Bednar would place his hands on [John’s] head and completely heal him of the cancer. I knew that through the power of the priesthood he could be healed, and I wanted so bad for that to happen. After he taught us about the faith to not be healed, I was terrified. Up to that point, I had never had to come to grips with the fact that the Lord’s plan might include losing my new husband. My faith was dependent upon the outcomes I wanted. In a manner of speaking, it was one-dimensional. Though terrifying at first, the thought of having the faith not to be healed ultimately freed me from worry. It allowed me to have complete trust that my Heavenly Father knew me better than I knew myself, and He would do what was best for me and John.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p45">A blessing was given, and weeks, months, and years passed by. John’s cancer miraculously went into remission. He was able to complete his university studies and obtained gainful employment. John and Heather continued to strengthen their relationship and enjoy life together.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p46">Some time later I subsequently received a letter from John and Heather informing me that the cancer had returned. Chemotherapy was resumed and surgery scheduled. John explained: “Not only did this news come as a disappointment to [Heather] and me, but we were puzzled by it. Was there something we did not learn the first time? Did the Lord expect something more from us? Growing up as Latter-day Saints, it was common to go to church and hear the phrase, ‘every trial God gives us is for our benefit.’ Well, to be honest, I could not see how this was benefitting me!</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p47">“So I began to pray for clarity and for the Lord to help me understand why this recurrence of the cancer was happening. One day as I was reading in the New Testament I received my answer. I read the account of Christ and His Apostles on the sea when a tempest arose. Fearing the boat would capsize, the disciples went to the Savior and asked, ‘Master, carest thou not that we perish?’ This is exactly how I felt! Carest thou not that I have cancer? Carest thou not that we want to start a family? But as I read on in the story, I found my answer. The Lord looked at them and said, ‘O ye of little faith,’ and He stretched forth His hand and calmed the waters.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t3">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p48">“In that moment I had to ask myself, ‘Do I really believe this?’ Do I really believe He calmed the waters that day? Or is it just a nice story to read about?’ The answer is: I do believe, and because I know He calmed the waters, I instantly knew He could heal me. Up until this point, I had a hard time reconciling the need for my faith in Christ with the inevitability of His will. I saw them as two separate things, and sometimes I felt that one contradicted the other. ‘Why should I have faith if His will ultimately is what will prevail,’ I asked? After this experience, I knew that having faith—at least in my circumstance—was not necessarily knowing that He <i>would</i> heal me, but that He <i>could</i> heal me. I had to believe that He could, and then whether it happened was up to Him.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p49">“As I allowed those two ideas to coexist in my life, focused faith in Jesus Christ and complete submission to His will, I found greater comfort and peace. It has been so remarkable to see the Lord’s hand in our lives. Things have fallen into place, miracles have happened, and we continually are humbled to see God’s plan for us unfold.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p50">I repeat for emphasis John’s statement: “As I allowed those two ideas to coexist in my life, focused faith in Jesus Christ and complete submission to His will, I found greater comfort and peace.”</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p51">Righteousness and faith certainly are instrumental in moving mountains—if moving mountains accomplishes God’s purposes and is in accordance with His will. Righteousness and faith certainly are instrumental in healing the sick, deaf, or lame—if such healing accomplishes God’s purposes and is in accordance with His will. Thus, even with strong faith, many mountains will not be moved. And not all of the sick and infirm will be healed. If all opposition were curtailed, if all maladies were removed, then the primary purposes of the Father’s plan would be frustrated.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p52">Many of the lessons we are to learn in mortality can only be received through the things we experience and sometimes suffer. And God expects and trusts us to face temporary mortal adversity with His help so we can learn what we need to learn and ultimately become what we are to become in eternity.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t4">
                    <div class="title">The Meaning of All Things</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p54">This story about John and Heather is both ordinary and extraordinary. This young couple is representative of millions of faithful, covenant-keeping Latter-day Saints all over the world who are pressing forward along the strait and narrow path with steadfast faith in Christ and a perfect brightness of hope. John and Heather were not serving in highly visible leadership positions in the Church, they were not related to General Authorities, and sometimes they had doubts and fears. In many of these aspects, their story is quite ordinary.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p55">But, brothers and sisters, this young man and young woman were blessed in extraordinary ways to learn essential lessons for eternity through affliction and hardship. I have shared this episode with you because John and Heather, who are just like so many of you, came to understand that not shrinking is more important than surviving. Thus, their experience was not primarily about living and dying; rather, it was about learning, living, and becoming.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p56">The potent spiritual combination of faith in and on the holy name of Jesus Christ, of meekly submitting to His will and timing, of pressing forward “with unwearied diligence” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/hel/15.6" class="scriptureRef">Helaman 15:6</a>), and of acknowledging His hand in all things yields the peaceable things of the kingdom of God that bring joy and eternal life (see <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/42.61" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 42:61</a>). As this couple faced seemingly overwhelming challenges, they lived a “peaceable life in all godliness and honesty” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/1-tim/2.2" class="scriptureRef">1 Timothy 2:2</a>). They walked peaceably (see <a href="/scriptures/bofm/moro/7.4" class="scriptureRef">Moroni 7:4</a>) with and among the children of men. “And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, [kept their] hearts and minds through Christ Jesus” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/philip/4.7" class="scriptureRef">Philippians 4:7</a>).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p57">For many of you, their story is, has been, or could be your story. You are facing, have faced, or will yet face equivalent challenges in your lives with the same courage and spiritual perspective that John and Heather did. I do not know why some people learn the lessons of eternity through trial and suffering—while others learn similar lessons through rescue and healing. I do not know all of the reasons, all of the purposes, and I do not know everything about the Lord’s timing. With Nephi, you and I can say that we “do not know the meaning of all things” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/11.17" class="scriptureRef">1 Nephi 11:17</a>).</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t5">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p58">But some things I absolutely do know. I know we are spirit sons and daughters of a loving Heavenly Father. I know the Eternal Father is the author of the plan of happiness. I know Jesus Christ is our Savior and Redeemer. I know Jesus enabled the Father’s plan through His infinite and eternal Atonement. I know that the Lord, who was “bruised, broken, [and] torn for us” (“Jesus of Nazareth, Savior and King,” <i>Hymns</i>, no. 181), can succor and strengthen “his people according to their infirmities” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/7.12" class="scriptureRef">Alma 7:12</a>). And I know one of the greatest blessings of mortality is to not shrink and to allow our individual will to be “swallowed up in the will of the Father” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/15.7" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 15:7</a>).</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.t6">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p59">Though I do not know everything about how and when and where and why these blessings occur, I do know and I witness they are real. I testify that all of these things are true—and that we know enough by the power of the Holy Ghost to bear sure witness of their divinity, reality, and efficacy. My beloved brothers and sisters, I invoke upon you this blessing: even that as you press forward in your lives with steadfast faith in Christ, you will have the capacity to not shrink. I bear this witness and I invoke this blessing in the sacred name of the Lord Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
                </block>
            </div>
            <!--<div class="notes">
                <div class="title">Notes</div>
            </div>-->
            <div class="resources">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/that-we-might-not-shrink-d-c-19-18.p61">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 8/12. testPD00045417 000</block>
                </block>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00045417.002" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00045417_000_002.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>Have I Seen the Hand of God in My Life?</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00045417_000_002</source>
                <item-number>testPD00045417</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>faith</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-03-21T14:02:00.228-06:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author>
                        <author-name>Sister Susan Bednar</author-name>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.head1">
                <h1>Have I Seen the Hand of God in My Life?</h1>
                <div class="authorName">Sister Susan Bednar</div>
                <div class="event">CES Devotional for Young Adults • March 3, 2013 • University of Texas Arlington</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p4">As I travel the world with my husband, I’m saddened to discover that many young people feel alone and doubt that the Lord knows them personally or loves them. I’ve prayed about the principles I could emphasize tonight that would help you know the Lord does know you and love you. I pray for the Spirit to help me deliver this message.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p5">I am going to use words from a seminary song to organize my remarks:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.f1">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">We must have ears to hear the word of the Lord,</div>
                        <div class="line">And eyes to see His plan,</div>
                        <div class="line">Feet to follow in His path,</div>
                        <div class="line">And hearts to understand.</div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.f2">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">(Steven K. Jones, “Hearts that Understand,” <i>Hold to the Rod Songbook</i> [1988], 20)</div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.t1">
                    <div class="title">Ears to Hear the Word of the Lord</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p12">First, we must have ears to hear the word of the Lord. We can hear the voice of the Lord as we study the scriptures (see <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/18.34-36" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 18:34–36</a>). When I was your age, Spencer W. Kimball was the President of the Church. A quote from him has guided me throughout my life. He said: “I find that when I get casual in my relationships with divinity and when it seems that no divine ear is listening and no divine voice is speaking, that I am far, far away. If I immerse myself in the scriptures the distance narrows and the spirituality returns” (<i>Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Spencer W</i>.<i> Kimball</i> [2006], 67).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p13">I testify that if we have ears to hear the word of the Lord, we will feel His love as He speaks to us through the scriptures.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.t2">
                    <div class="title">Eyes to See His Plan</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p15">Second, we must have eyes to see His plan. One day I was thinking about a returned missionary I knew when, unexpectedly, I received an email from her. She told me how she felt the Lord working miracles through her in the mission field, but since her return home she wondered sometimes if He was really aware of her.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p16">In my answer to her, I shared some important counsel Elder Henry B. Eyring gave to BYU–Idaho students. He said: “I bless you that every day, if you will ask in prayer to be shown where the hand of God intervened in your life that day, I bless you that you will see that. It will be made manifest to you. That you will see that He is leading and guiding and lifting you, and that He knows you” (“A Steady, Upward Course” [Brigham Young University–Idaho devotional, Sept. 18, 2001], web.byui.edu/devotionalsandspeeches).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p17">I then explained how I prayed daily for this blessing and had seen the hand of God reaching out to touch me through her thoughtful note. I reassured her Heavenly Father would do the same for her.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p18">I testify, as we pray for eyes to see His plan, we will be aware of God’s involvement in our lives and know that He knows us.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.t3">
                    <div class="title">Feet to Follow in His Path</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p20">Third, we must have feet to follow in His path. Many young adults become disillusioned, disheartened, and discouraged because events they thought would happen in their lives have not yet occurred. Some mistakenly believe if God hasn’t given them the happiness or blessings they were hoping for or thought they deserved, He doesn’t care. To show their displeasure with God, some lose faith, dishonor covenants, put their trust in worldly pleasures, and turn from God to self. Instead of having feet to follow the path of righteousness, they deviate from the gospel path, wander off, and become lost. We all know someone who is “off the path.” We can feel God’s love in our lives as we see the positive reaction of many as we reach out to serve and to rescue.</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p21">The Lord’s path is clearly marked by the teachings of prophets, seers, and revelators. Next month is general conference. I testify, if we prayerfully seek to identify a personal question or concern to take to conference, the Lord will answer us through the messages of His anointed servants. We will feel His love and concern and have increased courage and steady feet to follow in His path now and forever.</block>
                </block>
                <block type="topic" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.t4">
                    <div class="title">Hearts to Understand</div>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p23">Fourth, we need hearts to understand the gift of the Atonement of Jesus Christ. Elder Bednar has taught: “It is one thing to know that Jesus Christ came to earth to <i>die</i> for us—that is fundamental and foundational to the doctrine of Christ. But we also need to appreciate that the Lord desires, through His Atonement and by the power of the Holy Ghost, to <i>live</i> in us—not only to direct us but also to empower us” (“The Atonement and the Journey of Mortality,” <i>Ensign</i>, Apr. 2012, 42).</block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p24">To me, the Atonement of Jesus Christ provides individual comfort and powerful evidence of God’s love for us. It strengthens us to do hard things—things we do not think we can do. It helps us hold on when we do not understand God’s will and timing in our lives. I testify God lives, and we will feel His love and know that He knows us as we dedicate our hearts to understand more fully the blessings of the Atonement of His Son, Jesus Christ.</block>
                    <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.f3">
                        <div class="stanza">
                            <div class="line">We must have ears to hear the word of the Lord,</div>
                            <div class="line">And eyes to see His plan,</div>
                            <div class="line">Feet to follow in His path,</div>
                            <div class="line">And hearts to understand.</div>
                            <div class="line">(Jones, “Hearts that Understand,” 20)</div>
                        </div>
                    </block>
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p30">In the name of Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
                </block>
            </div>
            <div class="resources">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/have-i-seen-the-hand-of-god-in-my-life.p31">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 8/12. Language. testPD00045417 000</block>
                </block>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00045139.011" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00045139_000_11.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>Our Prophet Thomas S Monson</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">our-prophet-thomas-s-monson</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00045139_000_11</source>
                <item-number>testPD00045139</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>Thomas S. Monson</subject>
                    <subject>follow the prophet</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-06-10T09:58:47.915129-06:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author uri="/church/leader/william-r-walker">
                        <author-name>William R. Walker</author-name>
                        <author-title>Of the Seventy</author-title>
                        <author-role value="seventy" translate="no" living="1">Seventy</author-role>
                        <author-rank translate="no">05</author-rank>
                        <author-seniority translate="no">999</author-seniority>
                        <image type="jpg" uri="william-r-walker-10.jpg" translate="no"/>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.head1">
                <h1>Our Prophet: Thomas S. Monson</h1>
                <div class="authorName">William R. Walker</div>
                <div class="event">CES Devotional for Young Adults • May 5, 2013 • Brigham Young University–Idaho</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p5">“We Thank Thee, O God, for a Prophet” (<i>Hymns,</i> no. 19). This hymn is one of the hallmarks of the Church. We <i>do</i> thank God for a prophet to guide us in these latter days.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p6">That God has provided a prophet for us is <i>central</i> to the faith and belief of Latter-day Saints everywhere. We know that God lives and that He loves us. We know that He sent His Son, Jesus Christ, to be our Savior and Redeemer, and we know that He has given us a prophet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p7">Those who lived in the early days of the Church felt deep gratitude to have lived during the time of the Prophet Joseph Smith. The messages and testimonies of the Restoration were often firsthand experiences for the early Saints.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p8">Marvelous things happened during the years that Brigham Young presided over the Lord’s Church. The Saints came west and established themselves in the heart of the Rocky Mountains, where the Church flourished. Those who lived during that time counted it as a great blessing to have lived during the time of the prophet Brigham Young.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p9">This same pattern continued as the Lord provided great and noble men to direct the affairs of His Church. My parents and grandparents spoke with deep reverence and fondness of the prophet of their day—President Heber J. Grant.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p10">For Sister Walker and me, and for many of your parents and grandparents, we loved the great example and remarkable teachings of the prophet David O. McKay. He was followed by his successors: Joseph Fielding Smith, Harold B. Lee, Spencer W. Kimball, Ezra Taft Benson, and Howard W. Hunter. Each man was wonderfully prepared to lead the Church for a period of time determined by the Lord Himself. Each of them were loved and sustained by the members of the Church.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p11">Most of you here this evening will fondly remember the great leadership of President Gordon B. Hinckley. What a blessing to have lived during his time as President of the Church.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p12">Five years ago the Lord called President Hinckley home and Thomas S. Monson became the President of the Church—the Lord’s prophet on the earth today. Oh, what a blessing it is for you and me to live in this wonderful day when we are led by such a great prophet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p13">This is the Lord’s Church. He plans the lives of these great Apostles, and He places them in the position to lead His Church. It is a fact that one of the distinguishing characteristics of the Lord’s Church is that He has apostles and prophets on the earth today.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p14">The Apostle Paul described the Church as having “apostles and prophets, [with] Jesus Christ himself being the chief corner stone” (Ephesians 2:20). So it was, and so it is. The Lord’s Church is distinguished by having apostles and prophets, with Jesus Christ Himself being the chief cornerstone. Every President of the Church has testified that Jesus Christ is the head of this Church.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p15">There are no coincidences, there are no mistakes, and there are no campaigns. When it comes to succession in the Presidency of the Lord’s Church, the Lord is in charge, and surely His will is done.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p16">I testify to you that it is the will of the Lord that we are led today by President Thomas S. Monson, who <i>is</i> the Lord’s prophet on the earth today.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p17">As the Old Testament prophet Jeremiah taught us about prophets, we know this to be true with President Monson. The scripture says, “Before I formed thee in the belly I knew thee; and before thou camest forth out of the womb I sanctified thee, and I ordained thee a prophet unto the nations” (<a href="/scriptures/ot/jer/1.5" class="scriptureRef">Jeremiah 1:5</a>).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p18">I want to speak to you today about the life and ministry of President Thomas S. Monson, the 16th President of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p19">During the last year of President Hinckley’s life, he appointed me to be the Executive Director of the Temple Department, and President Monson has honored me by allowing me to remain in this assignment. Over the last six years, I have had the great and unforgettable blessing of assisting President Thomas S. Monson and his counselors on temple matters. I have sat at his side as President Monson has given me much counsel and direction about temples and temple matters throughout the world. He has invited me to accompany him to temple dedications, groundbreakings, and visits to prospective temple sites. I have had the blessing of traveling with him around the world, to places as far away as Kyiv, in the Ukraine, and Cebu, in the Philippines, and to other exciting places, like Rome, Italy.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p20">As he has crisscrossed the world, I’ve been blessed to be there to witness his great love for people—not just members of the Church, but all people. I’ve witnessed his constant warmth and friendliness, his Christlike tenderness and sensitivity, especially for the children, the aged, and the infirm. Many times as I’ve watched President Monson, I’ve had the impression: “That is the way the Savior would act. That is the way the Savior would treat people.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p21">I have witnessed his never-ending enthusiasm, his drive and determination, his joy in life, and his deep desire to serve the Lord and do as the Savior would have him do. He never tires of doing the work of the Lord.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p22">In the <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/52.14" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants, section 52, verse 14</a>, the Lord said, “I will give … you a pattern in all things, that ye may not be deceived.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p23">I love this scripture because it teaches me that the Lord will provide a pattern for me and show me how to do things, how to act, how to live. But it is not about me. It is about each of us. The Lord does show us the way. He does provide patterns in each of our lives to show us how to live.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p24">I believe one of the important patterns in our lives is the life of the prophet who guides and directs the Lord’s Church in our day. As I mentioned earlier, for me as a young person, the pattern was President David O. McKay. I loved him and sustained him, prayed for him, and studied his words carefully, and I wanted to be as much like him as I could imagine that I could be.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p25">I suspect that when many of your parents were young, their pattern was President Spencer W. Kimball. Of course, for each of us, our greatest desire is to pattern our life after the Savior—to follow Him, to live His commandments, and to be as much like Him as we can be.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p26">In <a href="/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/27.27" class="scriptureRef">3 Nephi 27:27</a>, Jesus taught: “What manner of men ought ye to be? Verily I say unto you, even as I am.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p27">That is our principal goal—to be like Him.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p28">Positioned on the wall of every office President Monson has occupied since being called as bishop has been a familiar print of the Savior painted by Heinrich Hofmann. It is a beautiful portrayal of the Savior.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p29">Speaking about this painting, President Monson said: “I love the painting, which I have had since I was a twenty-two-year-old bishop and which I have taken with me wherever I have been assigned to labor. I have tried to pattern my life after the Master. Whenever I have had a difficult decision to make, I have always looked at that picture and asked myself, ‘What would He do?’ Then I try to do it” (in Heidi S. Swinton, <i>To the Rescue: The Biography of Thomas S. Monson</i> [2010], 135).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p30">I know that President Monson thinks about following the example of Jesus. On one occasion I was with President Monson for an event prior to a temple dedication. He had just flown in that day, and as the evening meeting was drawing to a close, I thought President Monson might be tired, and I wanted to make sure he got some rest prior to the events of the next day. As the closing hymn was being sung, I leaned over to President Monson and said, “President, after the closing prayer, if we slip out the side door, we can get you back to the hotel quickly and you can get some rest.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p31">With a puzzled look, he said to me, “Elder Walker, if Jesus were here, do you think He would slip out the side door when the meeting ended?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p32">I haven’t made that suggestion again. Like the Savior would have done, he wanted to be with the people. He wasn’t thinking about himself at all. He was thinking about the good he could do.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p33">I have always felt that I can be a better person when I pattern my life after righteous individuals that the Lord has placed in my path: my grandparents, my parents, my bishops, my mission president, and of course, the prophet of God who I can see and hear and for whom I pray each day. I am sure that most of you do the same.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p34">It has been a wonderful blessing in my life to seek to be more like the Lord and to seek to be more like His prophet—President Thomas S. Monson.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p35">I would like to share with you some of the life and teachings of President Monson, and hopefully, as I do so, you will be able to identify characteristics that you will want to put into your life. We would all be blessed to seek to pattern our lives after and learn from the Lord’s prophet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p36">Like Nephi, and like most of you, Thomas S. Monson was born of goodly parents. He was born in Salt Lake City on August 21, 1927. He was raised in humble circumstances. He never tried to recharacterize where he was from. With his self-effacing sense of humor, combined with complete comfort with who he is, President Monson would occasionally say he didn’t need to worry about which side of the railroad tracks he was from because he grew up <i>between</i> the railroad tracks.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p37">I’ve always been impressed with how he has always spoken so fondly of his youth. I think he was a lot like Nephi. Laman and Lemuel were good at seeing the problems and looking at the negative side of everything, it seemed. Nephi, on the other hand, was positive, optimistic, and grateful. He saw the good in everything around him. That is the way Tommy Monson grew up—and he has been that way all of his life!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p38">He was a good student, and perhaps more importantly, he was a good boy. He showed his desire to do well in the service of the Lord when he was called to serve as secretary of the deacons quorum in his ward. Nearly 70 years later, as President of the Church, he reflected with some pride on his desire to make the minutes of his deacons quorum the best they could be. He had no thought about “Why am I the secretary and not the president of the quorum?” He just wanted to do his job well. He had been called to a position in the Lord’s Church, and he wanted to do his best. He wanted the minutes to be neat and orderly, and so he typed the minutes for his deacons quorum. As a 12-year-old boy, he was setting a wonderful example for us.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p39">If this sounds remarkable to you, I’m not surprised. It was also remarkable to his stake president who, when he heard of young Tommy’s excellent work, called on him to speak in stake conference—as the secretary of the deacons quorum. Have you ever heard of the secretary of a deacons quorum speaking in stake conference? What an example for all of us!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p40">He finished high school and joined the United States Navy. He served his country, and while doing so, he kept himself clean and virtuous. He returned from his military service and worked hard to get a good education. He was a good student—another great example for all of us! (The example of being a good student may be more important for some of you than for others.)</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p41">He courted and fell in love with a beautiful Latter-day Saint girl named Frances Johnson and soon afterward asked her to marry him. They were married in the Salt Lake Temple on October 7, 1948, at age 21. What an example for all of us! (Again, perhaps more important for some of you than for others.)</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p42">Although only married for 18 months, and while working to get ahead in a new job, he accepted the call from the Lord to serve as the bishop of a large inner-city ward. It was the ward in which he had grown up. (Think about that!) He didn’t say, “The timing is not right” or “I’m too young”; he just accepted the call, trusted in the Lord, and threw himself into the assignment with all the energy and talent that the Lord had given him. He wanted to be the best he could be in the service of the Lord.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p43">Young Bishop Monson came to love a scripture that can bless each of our lives, as it blessed his life:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p44">“Trust in the Lord with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own understanding.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p45">“In all thy ways acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy paths” (<a href="/scriptures/ot/prov/3.5-6" class="scriptureRef">Proverbs 3:5–6</a>).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p46">To this day, President Monson cites that scripture often and lives his life in accordance with what it teaches us. What an example he is for all of us! We would all do well if we remembered that scripture and made it an important part of our philosophy of life—just as President Monson has done.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p47">Bishop Monson’s ward had over 1,000 members, including 84 widows. We have been blessed in general conference and other settings to occasionally hear him tell some of the sweet experiences he had as he nurtured these sisters who were blessed to come under his care.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p48">For me, every time I hear him speak of one of his experiences as bishop, I realize, and it is very impressive to me, that his love and concern for the members of his ward did not end when he was released as bishop. He was called into the stake presidency at age 27, but even many years later (after his call as a mission president and an Apostle), he continued to love, nurture, and look out for the older members of his ward. He was clearly not just loving and caring for them by assignment. His love and concern for them sank deep into his heart and could not be taken away by any change of assignment.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p49">In this, President Monson has shown us the way. It is a better way; it is the Lord’s way. He loves others and is concerned for others—just as the Lord taught us that we should be. What an example he is for all of us!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p50">At age 31, President Monson was called to be president of the Canadian Mission, headquartered in Toronto, Ontario. Just as he had done as bishop, he threw himself into his assignment, gave it everything he had, and trusted in the Lord with all his heart. Everyone around him could see his love for the Lord, his love for his wife and children, his love for the missionaries and the members, and his love for Canada, the land where he had been called to serve. His influence as mission president was profound and to this day cannot be measured. His missionaries loved him and sought to live lives that would make their mission president proud. We can all learn from that.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p51">Just as he did when he was released as bishop, he continued to hold dear in his heart his feelings and affection for his missionaries and the Saints who had been blessed to come under his stewardship. I have been a witness to President Monson’s never-diminishing affection and interest in the missionaries who served under him in the Canadian Mission. What an example!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p52">I know the missionaries who were blessed to have Thomas S. Monson as their mission president have tried to follow the pattern of righteous service in the Lord’s kingdom that President and Sister Monson modeled for them. To illustrate, I share with you the remarkable fact that of the 141 temple presidents currently serving throughout the world, five of them were young missionaries who served under President Monson in the Canadian Mission.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p53">Thousands of you who are with us this evening are returned missionaries. I pray that each of us will follow the example of these five temple presidents and strive to be faithful and walk the path of righteous service modeled by our mission presidents.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p54">I was touched recently to see a photo in the <i>Church News</i> of President Monson visiting a man in a Toronto, Canada, hospital (see “Teachings of the Prophet,” <i>Church News,</i> Feb. 3, 2013, 7). This gentleman had served at President Monson’s side 50 years earlier. President Monson had not forgotten him. Many years and many miles had not robbed President Monson of the sweet feelings of love and appreciation that come to those who serve the Lord together. I hope each of us will follow his example and not forget those who have blessed our lives in earlier years.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p55">In 1963, when he was 36 years old, Thomas S. Monson was invited to the office of President David O. McKay, who was the President of the Church at that time. It was at this meeting that President McKay called him to be an Apostle of the Lord Jesus Christ.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p56">President Monson is the only Apostle called to the Twelve at such a young age in the last 100 years. Surely, the hand of the Lord directed the call of this young Apostle because the Lord knew Thomas S. Monson would lead the Church in our day.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p57">This October general conference will be the 50th anniversary of Thomas S. Monson’s call to be an Apostle. How wonderful is that? (Not since Joseph Fielding Smith have we had an Apostle celebrate 50 years in the Twelve.)</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p58">For 22 years President Monson served as a counselor to three Presidents of the Church: Ezra Taft Benson, Howard W. Hunter, and Gordon B. Hinckley. On February 3, 2008, Thomas S. Monson was ordained and set apart as the President of the Church. He has two noble and great counselors who stand at his side: President Henry B. Eyring and President Dieter F. Uchtdorf. They are the three presiding high priests who direct the Lord’s Church on the earth today (see D&amp;C 107:22).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p59">President Monson’s remarkable ministry has often been characterized by the expression “to the rescue.” Heidi Swinton wrote a marvelous biography on his life, and she fittingly entitled it <i>To the Rescue.</i> The biography was published in 2010. If you haven’t read it, I highly recommend it to you. It will bless your life.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p60">The message, of course, is the same message that Jesus gave us in Luke: to leave the “ninety and nine” and go and rescue the one (<a href="/scriptures/nt/luke/15.4" class="scriptureRef">Luke 15:4</a>). This is the essence of the gospel of Jesus Christ, to love our fellowmen and to do all we can to bless their lives. President Monson has always taught these principles, but more importantly, he lives that way. His life has been filled with countless examples of reaching out to visit, comfort, or assist those most in need: the widows, the children, the sick, the afflicted, and those who are lonely or brokenhearted.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p61">The Apostle James wrote, “Pure religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, To visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep himself unspotted from the world” (<a href="/scriptures/nt/james/1.27" class="scriptureRef">James 1:27</a>).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p62">This is the way President Monson has lived his life. The lesson for us is that one does not need to be an Apostle to live this way. We can live our religion, we can visit the fatherless and the widows, and we can keep ourselves unspotted from the world. We can look to our prophet to see how we can do this! We can say to ourselves, “That is the kind of person I want to be.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p63">Several years ago, just before general conference, President Monson taught yet another wonderful lesson. This time it was to the assembled General Authorities, who had traveled to Salt Lake City, many coming from places around the world where they were serving in Area Presidencies. It was a very important meeting. We had come together to be instructed by the First Presidency and the Twelve.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p64">As the time for the meeting approached, everyone seemed to be in attendance except President Monson, who had not yet arrived. Several minutes before the meeting was to begin, we stopped visiting with each other and sat reverently listening to the prelude music—expecting that the prophet would come in at any moment.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p65">We patiently waited as the hour of 9:00 a.m. came and then passed. Someone walked out the side door—obviously to check and see if some assistance might be needed. On his reentrance into the room, we were told that “President Monson will join us shortly.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p66">About 15 minutes after the meeting was to have started, President Monson entered the room. Out of respect, we stood as he entered. We were happy to see him and pleased that he looked well. It did not appear that there was any obvious reason as to why he would have been late.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p67">President Monson went straight to the pulpit and said, “Brethren, I’m sorry to be late, but my wife needed me this morning.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p68">I was deeply impressed and humbled. I couldn’t quit thinking about President Monson’s words. This was a very important meeting. The entire senior leadership of the Church was assembled, but President Monson set the example for us all. His wife needed him, and he took the time necessary to care for her. It was a great sermon. I don’t remember anything else that was said that day, but I remember that sermon: “My wife needed me.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p69">This sermon was reinforced on another occasion when President Monson said, “When I hear men say they love their wives, then I want to say to them, ‘Then prove it by how you treat her and how you serve her.’”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p70">That is the way President Monson is: He is always looking out for someone else. He is always showing kindness and care for others.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p71">You don’t have to be around President Monson long to sense his deep love and commitment to his sweetheart, Sister Frances Monson. Whenever he speaks of her, his eyes light up and he gets a big smile on his face. You know this is a man whose love for his wife is an example to every one of us. President and Sister Monson have shown us the example of a man and a woman equally yoked in their love of the Lord and their desire to serve Him in righteousness.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p72">I want to be more like the Lord, but I also want to be more like His prophet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p73">If you wonder what President Monson might desire for each of you, maybe the sharing of the following experience will help you to know:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p74">Last November the beautiful Boise Idaho Temple was ready for rededication, following an 18-month closure to beautify and upgrade the temple. After 30 years of remarkable use by the faithful Saints in that part of Idaho and surrounding areas, the temple was in much need of repair. After it was completed, as has been customary, to celebrate the occasion of the temple rededication, the youth of the temple district were invited to put on a grand cultural celebration. It was an evening of singing and dancing and expressing their faith and gratitude for the temple.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p75">I was seated next to President Monson as we watched the wonderful presentations by the various stakes. One of the dance numbers featured a lovely group of young women. As President Monson was enjoying the performance, he leaned over to me and expressed the feelings of his heart. He said, “My hope would be for every one of them to have a temple marriage. I so much want each one of them to have that blessing—to be married in the temple.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p76">I thought: “Isn’t this wonderful. The prophet of God is here witnessing this youth celebration of song and dance, and for him it is very clearly connected to the temple that he would dedicate the next morning. His hope was for every one of them to have a temple marriage.” If that is the prophet’s desire for us, <i>and it is,</i> then each one of us should want that for ourselves, and it should be a very, very important goal in each of our lives.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p77">I would like to share another experience with you:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p78">President Monson, President Eyring, and Elder Quentin L. Cook of the Quorum of the Twelve traveled to Laie, Hawaii, for the rededication of that magnificent temple in November of 2010. The night before the temple dedication, we were assembled in the Cannon Center on the BYU–Hawaii campus for the cultural celebration. The program was wonderful. Through song, dance, and narrative, the youth of the temple district told the story of the history of the Church in Hawaii. They told of the early missionaries and the early converts. They told the remarkable story of the future prophet Joseph F. Smith being called to serve a mission in Hawaii in 1854, when he was only 15 years of age. Young Joseph F. Smith returned from his three-year mission just before his 19th birthday. (And you thought the recent age change to 18 was remarkable, didn’t you?)</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p79">The cultural celebration continued as the youth portrayed the growth of the Church among the Polynesian people and told how President Joseph F. Smith returned to Hawaii over 50 years later and, as the President of the Church, dedicated the site and broke ground for the construction of the Laie Hawaii Temple.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p80">The cultural celebration was wonderful, and President Monson loved every bit of it. He enjoyed a performance that featured the popular World War II dance number “Boogie Woogie Bugle Boy” because it reminded him of his days in the United States Navy. Other numbers focused on the various dances of the island people.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p81">A number featuring the beautiful hula dance was performed. One of the young women involved in this dance was in a wheelchair. She was very pretty, and even though she didn’t have the use of her legs, she performed the dance beautifully. President Monson pointed her out to me and commented on how lovely she was and how beautifully she was doing the dance.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p82">As the program ended, everyone was happy about the great performances given. As we left the stand, all of the dancers were back on the floor, including the hula dancers. President Monson didn’t follow the planned exit route but went straight to the floor to express his appreciation to the youth, and in particular he went straight to the beautiful girl in the wheelchair to commend her and express his love to her.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p83">Even in the midst of the celebration and the large crowd, President Monson again showed the pure love of the Savior. He went to the one. He bent down and kissed her on the forehead. I thought: “Isn’t this wonderful. Once again the prophet of God is showing us how to reach out to those around us, how to be kind and loving, and how to encourage and to lift.” I thought: “This is the way Jesus would act. This is the way the Savior would want us to treat others.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p84">I love the Primary song that says, “I’m trying to be like Jesus” (“I’m Trying to Be Like Jesus,” <i>Children's Songbook,</i> 78). And I want to add to that, “And I’m trying to be like His prophet.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p85">I would like to suggest five ways we can follow the example of President Monson:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p86">
                    <i>First, we can be positive, and we can be happy.</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p87">In the Pearl of Great Price, the Prophet Joseph Smith is described as having a cheery countenance (see Joseph Smith—History 1:28). That also describes President Monson. He really has a cheery countenance.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p88">On one occasion President Monson said: “We … can choose to have a positive attitude. We can’t direct the wind, but we can adjust the sails. In other words, we can choose to be happy and positive, regardless of what comes our way” (“Messages of Inspiration from President Monson,” <i>Church News,</i> Sept. 2, 2012, 2).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p89">One day I was waiting outside the First Presidency boardroom. I had been invited there to take part in a meeting to discuss temple matters. I quietly sat outside the room, alone. I thought the First Presidency was already meeting and that I would be invited to join them in a few minutes. As I sat there I could hear someone walking down the hall whistling. I thought to myself: “Someone doesn’t understand proper protocol. You don’t go walking around whistling outside the office of the President of the Church.” A moment later the whistler walked around the corner—it was President Monson. He was happy, and he was positive. He greeted me warmly and said, “I guess we’ll start the meeting in a couple of minutes.” Even with the weight of the whole Church on his shoulders, he is an example of happiness and he always has a positive attitude. We should be that way.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p90">
                    <i>Second, we can be kind and loving toward children, the way President Monson is.</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p91">Jesus spoke often of children. His prophet, President Monson, speaks often of children as well, and I’ve particularly seen at the temple dedications how he loves children and, by his example, teaches us how to treat them. At every temple dedication he focuses on the children. He loves to include them in the cornerstone ceremony and always invites a few of them to put some mortar in the cornerstone to participate in the symbolic completion of the temple. He makes it fun for them. He makes it memorable for them. He always has a big smile for them. He encourages and commends them. It is a wonderful thing to see.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p92">His warm greetings occasionally include high fives, wiggling of his ears, and encouragement to serve missions and marry in the temple. He really enjoys life—and shouldn’t we all.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p93">A few years ago President Monson was scheduled to dedicate the Oquirrh Mountain Temple on his birthday. As he arrived at the temple and approached the front door of the temple, a group of young people had assembled. They obviously knew it was President Monson’s birthday because they began to sing “Happy Birthday” to him. He loved it. He stopped and faced them with a big smile on his face. He even started to wave his arms as if he was leading them in the singing. At the end they added the refrain “And many more.” President Monson loved that too, as he said to me, “That’s my favorite part.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p94">The children and the young people of the Church love him, and I think it is because they have no doubt that he loves them! Jesus loved the little children, and His prophet loves the little children. That is a great example for each of us!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p95">
                    <i>Third, we can follow the promptings of the Spirit, like President Monson.</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p96">President Monson’s devotion to the Lord and his commitment to following the promptings of the Spirit were beautifully stated by the prophet himself with these words: “The sweetest experience I know in life is to feel a prompting and act upon it and later find out that it was the fulfillment of someone’s prayer or someone’s need. And I always want the Lord to know that if He needs an errand run, Tom Monson will run that errand for Him” (<i>On the Lord’s Errand</i> [DVD, 2008]). That is a pattern that each of us should want to follow.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p97">
                    <i>Fourth, we can love the temple, as President Monson loves the temple.</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p98">President Monson will go down in history as one of the great temple builders in the history of the Church. Since becoming President of the Church in February 2008, he has continued the great work of building temples. Some of the temples that he has announced have been among the most historic: “This morning I am pleased to announce five new temples for which sites have been acquired and which, in coming months and years, will be built in the following locations: Calgary, Alberta, Canada; Córdoba, Argentina; the greater Kansas City area; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and Rome, Italy” (Thomas S. Monson, “Welcome to Conference,” <i>Ensign</i> or <i>Liahona,</i> Nov. 2008, 6).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p99">In the five years that he has been the prophet, President Monson has announced plans to build 33 new temples. Just last month, in April conference, he announced plans for two new temples: one in Cedar City, Utah, and one in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p100">With the dedication of the Tegucigalpa Honduras Temple in March, we now have 141 temples in the Church, with another 29 currently under construction or in the planning stages. This is a great time of temple building and temple worship in the Lord’s Church. I’ve heard President Monson tell young people who were too young to enter the temple to go up and touch the wall of the temple and then “let the temple touch you.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p101">President Monson has said, “May each of us live worthy lives, with clean hands and pure hearts, so that the temple may touch our lives and our families” (“Blessings of the Temple,” <i>Ensign,</i> Oct. 2010, 19).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p102">He also gave this wonderful promise: “As we love the temple, touch the temple, and attend the temple, our lives will reflect our faith. As we come to these holy houses of God, as we remember the covenants we make within, <i>we shall be able to bear every trial and overcome each temptation</i>” (<i>Be Your Best Self</i> [1979], 56; emphasis added).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p103">Let us follow the pattern that the prophet has set for us in loving the temple.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p104">
                    <i>Fifth, we can be kind, considerate, and love others, as President Monson does.</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p105">President Monson is a wonderful example of loving others. His entire ministry has been filled with visits to homes; placing his hands on heads and giving blessings; making unexpected phone calls to comfort and encourage; sending letters of encouragement, commendation, and appreciation; visits to hospitals and care centers; and finding the time to go to funerals and viewings despite a very busy schedule.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p106">I mentioned earlier the 84 widows from President Monson’s ward when he was bishop. Over the decades that followed his service as bishop, in an incredible manifestation of dedication combined with the results of many of their prayers, President Monson was able to attend the funeral of every one of them. Just think about that.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p107">Just as the Savior would do, Thomas Monson has gone about doing good, blessing and loving others as if that has been the driving force in his life. We could all learn from this as <i>we</i> seek to follow in his footsteps.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p108">A remarkable example of President Monson’s kindness occurred last year. As the beautiful Brigham City Utah Temple was nearing completion, I met with the First Presidency to discuss plans for the dedication of the temple. With Brigham City being only one hour north of Salt Lake City, it would have been very easy for President Monson to travel there for the dedication. Instead, President Monson said, “Brigham City is the hometown of President Boyd K. Packer, this great Apostle who has sat beside me for so many years in the Twelve. I want him to have the honor and blessing of dedicating the temple in his hometown. I will stay away, and I’ll assign President Packer to dedicate the Brigham City Temple. I want it to be his day.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p109">It was a wonderful day for President Packer and for Sister Packer, who also grew up in Brigham City. I was very touched by President Monson’s kind and magnanimous gesture to his fellow Apostle. We can all be that way. We can share and be kind and not think of ourselves so much—but think more of those around us.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p110">I love the children’s song “Follow the Prophet.” It has nine wonderful verses, but I only have time to read the last verse:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.f1">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">Now we have a world where people are confused.</div>
                        <div class="line">If you don’t believe it, go and watch the news.</div>
                        <div class="line">We can get direction all along our way,</div>
                        <div class="line">If we heed the prophets—follow what they say.</div>
                        <div class="line">. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</div>
                        <div class="line">Follow the prophet; don’t go astray.</div>
                        <div class="line">. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</div>
                        <div class="line">Follow the prophet; he knows the way.</div>
                        <div class="line">(<i>Children’s Songbook,</i> 111)</div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p120">President Monson does know the way. The right way is the Lord’s way. “The right way is to believe in Christ” (<a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/25.29" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 25:29</a>).</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p121">President Monson has taught us the way to live our lives with his wonderful and inspiring messages at general conference. He has taught us how to be followers of Jesus Christ by his remarkable and wonderful personal example. Truly the Lord has given us a pattern in all things, and one of the patterns that we should seek to follow is that of our beloved prophet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p122">I testify that there is a God in heaven who knows us and loves us. He has given us a prophet—to guide us, to teach us, and to lead us in these latter days. I testify that Jesus Christ is the Son of God and the Savior of this world. I believe the Lord expects us to love the prophet, to sustain him, and to follow his example.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p123">We <i>do</i> thank Thee, O God, for a prophet. We thank Thee for <i>this</i> prophet. I count it as a great blessing to have lived in the day when Thomas S. Monson was the Lord’s prophet. As we follow the prophet and try to be more like him, we will inevitably succeed in being more faithful disciples of the Lord Jesus Christ.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p124">It has been an honor to speak to you this evening, and I pray the Lord will bless each of you abundantly, as I testify that this is the Lord’s work, in the name of Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
            </div>
            <!--<div class="notes">
                <div class="title">Notes</div>
            </div>-->
            <div class="resources">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/our-prophet-thomas-s-monson.p126">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 9/12. testPD00045139</block>
                </block>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00048932.011" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00048932_000_11.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>Youth of the Noble Birthright: What Will You Choose?</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00048932_000_11</source>
                <item-number>testPD00048932</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>agency</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-09-30T07:54:52.686312-06:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author uri="/church/leader/russell-m-nelson">
                        <author-name>Russell M. Nelson</author-name>
                        <author-title>Of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles</author-title>
                        <author-role value="twelve" translate="no" living="1">Twelve</author-role>
                        <author-rank translate="no">03</author-rank>
                        <author-seniority translate="no">03</author-seniority>
                        <image type="jpg" uri="russell-m-nelson-10.jpg" translate="no"/>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.head11">
                <h1>Youth of the Noble Birthright: What Will You Choose?</h1>
                <div class="authorName">Elder Russell M. Nelson</div>
                <div class="authorRole">Of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles</div>
                <div class="event">CES Devotional for Young Adults • September 6, 2013 • Brigham Young University–Hawaii</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p5">My wife, Wendy, and I are very grateful to be with you. From the Cannon Activities Center on the campus of BYU–Hawaii, we are broadcasting to congregations of young adults throughout the entire world. We extend a special welcome to those who are attending a CES devotional for the first time. As you enroll in institutions of higher learning, you will want to participate in institute classes and these devotionals to maintain a spiritual balance to your secular learning. And if you are soon headed for a mission, we are most grateful. You will be in the Lord’s service full time.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p6">I bring greetings and love from President Thomas S. Monson, President Henry B. Eyring, President Dieter F. Uchtdorf, and my beloved associates in the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles. I also bring greetings from the Board of Trustees of the Church Educational System and from Elder Paul V. Johnson, Commissioner of the Church Educational System.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p7">We have had three previous speakers at our CES devotionals this year. Do you remember them? President Dieter F. Uchtdorf’s talk was entitled “What Is Truth?” He taught us how to find real truth in an age when so much information is available, much of which is not true. The title of Elder David A. Bednar’s talk was “That We Might ‘Not … Shrink’ (<a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/19.18" class="scriptureRef">D&amp;C 19:18</a>).” He strengthened our spirits as he taught us how to increase our faith through a powerful question that helped a young couple as the husband battled cancer. The question posed by Elder Bednar was, “Do you have the faith not to be healed?” Elder William R. Walker strengthened our testimonies about the ministry and matchless example of our beloved President, Thomas S. Monson.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p8">Today, the title of my message is “Youth of the Noble Birthright<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="1"><a href="#1">1</a></sup>: What Will You Choose?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p9">You, as youth of the noble birthright, are literally sons and daughters of God, born at this particular time in the world’s history for a most sacred purpose. Although the moral and religious values of society seem to be weakening across the globe, youth of this Church are to be standard bearers of the Lord and beacons of light to attract others to Him. Your identity and purpose are unique.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p10">What is your identity? You are children of the covenant. What covenant? That which God made with Father Abraham when Abraham was promised that “in thy seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="2"><a href="#2">2</a></sup> You are also children of the promised day,<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="3"><a href="#3">3</a></sup> this period of world history when the gospel will be broadly proclaimed across the entire planet.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p11">What is your purpose? You brethren were foreordained in a premortal realm to bear the priesthood.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="4"><a href="#4">4</a></sup> Think of that! And you, dear sisters, were chosen before the foundation of the world to bear and care for God’s children, and in doing so, you glorify God.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="5"><a href="#5">5</a></sup> Have you sisters considered what it really means to be cocreators with God?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p12">Each of you young men and young women was commissioned by your Heavenly Father to build up the kingdom of God on earth right now and prepare a people to receive the Savior when He will rule and reign as the Millennial Messiah. Your noble birthright, identity, purpose, and divine commission set you apart from all others.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p13">But neither your birthright nor your premortal ordinations and commissions can save or exalt you. That you will do through your individual decisions and as you choose to access the power of the Lord’s Atonement in your lives. You know that “ev’ry soul is free / To choose his life and what he’ll be.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="6"><a href="#6">6</a></sup> That great eternal principle of agency is vital to our Father’s plan. So, you youth of the noble birthright, what will you choose?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p14">
                    <i>Will you choose to increase in learning?</i>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p15">Education is yours to obtain. No one else can gain it for you. Wherever you are, develop a deep desire to learn. For us as Latter-day Saints, gaining an education is not just a privilege, it is a religious responsibility. The glory of God is intelligence.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="7"><a href="#7">7</a></sup> Indeed, our education is for the eternities.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p16">“Whatever principle of intelligence we attain unto in this life, it will rise with us in the resurrection.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p17">“And if a person gains more knowledge and intelligence in this life … , he [or she] will have so much the advantage in the world to come.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="8"><a href="#8">8</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p18">Such a long-range perspective will help you make good choices about learning. I remember a conversation many years ago with a very bright 16-year-old high school student. He was uncertain about his religious commitment and undecided about his career. He wondered about the possibility of becoming a doctor of medicine. He asked me a simple question: “How many years did it take for you to become a heart surgeon?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p19">I quickly made the calculations: “From the time I graduated from high school until I first collected a fee for service as a surgeon, it took me 14 years.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p20">“Wow!” he replied. “That’s too long for me!”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p21">Then I asked, “How old will you be 14 years from now if you don’t become a heart surgeon?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p22">“Just the same,” he replied. “Just the same!”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p23">I had a special interest in this young man. On occasion I took him in my car on his early-morning route to deliver newspapers. Over the years his faith became strong. He was a powerful missionary. He decided to pursue his educational goal. First, he married his sweetheart in the temple. Then, while he studied medicine and surgery, they became the parents of four wonderful children. Now he is fully board certified as a heart surgeon—after intensive education and training over a period of 14 years.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p24">Brothers and sisters, don’t be afraid to pursue your goals—even your dreams! There is no shortcut to excellence and competence. Education is the difference between <i>wishing</i> you could help other people and <i>being able</i> to help them.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p25">Here is another question: <i>What manner of living will you choose?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p26">You, as youth of the noble birthright, are expected to live differently than others. You know what Paul said to young Timothy: “Be thou an example of the believers, in word, in conversation, in charity, in spirit, in faith, in purity.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="9"><a href="#9">9</a></sup> Choose to think and act differently than those of the world. Choose to look different and see what an influence for good you will become. As Sister Ardeth G. Kapp once said, “You can’t be a life saver if you look like all the other swimmers on the beach.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="10"><a href="#10">10</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p27">As youth of the noble birthright, you have a great start in life. But you also have an additional responsibility. “For of him [or her] unto whom much is given much is required.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="11"><a href="#11">11</a></sup> Part of that requirement is to be a recruit. Have you ever thought of yourself as an army recruit? When you were baptized, you were actually reenlisted in the Lord’s army.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="12"><a href="#12">12</a></sup> Premortally, you stood by Jesus Christ during the War in Heaven. And now the conflict between the forces of good and evil continues here on earth. It is real! That conflict in which we are now engaged is still between the forces of good and the forces of evil.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="13"><a href="#13">13</a></sup> On God’s side is Jesus Christ, foreordained to be the Savior of the world.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="14"><a href="#14">14</a></sup> On the other side is Satan—a rebel, a destroyer of agency.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="15"><a href="#15">15</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p28">God’s plan allows the adversary to tempt you so that you, now in this mortal world, can exercise your agency to choose good over evil, to choose to repent, to choose to come unto Jesus Christ and believe His teachings and follow His example. What a huge responsibility and a huge trust!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p29">Your freedom to choose is clearly explained in the Book of Mormon: “Men are free according to the flesh. … They are free to choose liberty and eternal life … or to choose captivity and death, according to the captivity and power of the devil; for he seeketh that all men might be miserable like unto himself.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="16"><a href="#16">16</a></sup> What will you choose?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p30">Another verse reveals that “wickedness never was happiness.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="17"><a href="#17">17</a></sup> Many youth have tried to challenge that truth and have failed every time.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p31">Your freedom to act for yourself is so central to your eternal progress and happiness that the adversary exerts extraordinary efforts to undermine it.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="18"><a href="#18">18</a></sup> Satan truly is an incorrigible insomniac, which means he never sleeps. Many of you have already experienced that!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p32">Here is another question: <i>Will you establish priorities to help you make your choices in life?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p33">Your choices will not all be between good and evil. Many will be choices between two good options. Not all truths are created equal, so you will need to establish priorities. In your pursuit of knowledge, know that the most important truth you can learn comes from the Lord. In His Intercessory Prayer to His Father, the Savior Himself confirmed this. He said, “This is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="19"><a href="#19">19</a></sup> Above everything else you are seeking to learn, seek to know God, your Heavenly Father, and His Son, Jesus Christ. Come to know Them and love Them, as I do.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p34">Another priority scripture that has helped me throughout my life is this one: “Seek ye first to build up the kingdom of God, and to establish his righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="20"><a href="#20">20</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p35">More than anything else in this world, you want to make choices that lead to the ultimate and glorious destiny of eternal life. That is God’s great glory for you.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="21"><a href="#21">21</a></sup> Choose eternal life as your highest priority! Study the scriptures, such as sections 76 and 88 of the Doctrine and Covenants, in order to understand more about the different blessings awaiting those who choose eternal life and those who don’t. Choose eternal life as your highest priority and notice how other choices fall into place.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p36">Another question: <i>With whom will you choose to associate?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p37">As youth of the noble birthright, you will mingle with many good people who also believe in God. Whether they be Jewish, Catholic, Protestant, or Muslim, believers know that there actually is absolute truth. In President Uchtdorf’s earlier message, he stressed that there really is right and wrong, and the willful breaking of one of God’s commandments really is sin. Believers in God also have a conscience. Believers obey civil and divine law voluntarily, even laws that might otherwise be unenforceable.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p38">With your commitment to obey civil and divine law, you stop for a red light, even if no other traffic is in sight. You, as a child of God, know that even if the police don’t catch you, that if you were to steal, murder, or commit adultery, these acts are wrong, and God will ultimately hold you accountable. You know that the consequences for not playing by the rules are not only temporal but eternal.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p39">As you move along life’s journey, you will also become acquainted with people who do not believe in God. Many of them have not yet found divine truth and don’t know where to look for it. But you youth of the noble birthright are coming to their rescue. In great numbers, you are rallying to the call of God’s prophet for more missionaries. We are deeply grateful for each one! Many of you have already served; others are preparing to go.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p40">As you mingle with nonbelievers, be aware that there may be a few who do not have your best interest at heart.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="22"><a href="#22">22</a></sup> As soon as you make that judgment—as soon as you discern that—flee from them quickly and permanently.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="23"><a href="#23">23</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p41">Sadly, you will meet people whose desperate search for something that seems to them like happiness takes them down the slippery slopes of sin. Beware of that slimy slide! Any pleasure in sin is only fleeting, and haunting memories are smeared by gnawing and grinding guilt. The sinful warping of the embrace divinely designed to unite husband and wife is but a hollow counterfeit. Each unlawful experience is stripped of deep meaning and sweet memory.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p42">One more question: <i>Will you choose freedom or bondage?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p43">Godless forces are all around. You are literally living in enemy-occupied territory.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="24"><a href="#24">24</a></sup> A plague of poisonous pornography abounds. It ensnares all who yield to its insidious grasp.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p44">This was foreseen by the Lord, who said, “And now I show unto you a mystery, a thing which is had in secret chambers, to bring to pass even your destruction in process of time, and ye knew it not.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="25"><a href="#25">25</a></sup> Then He added a second warning: “And again, I say unto you that the enemy in the secret chambers seeketh your lives.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="26"><a href="#26">26</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p45">Consider how many people, in however many secret chambers, are seeking to destroy your life and happiness! If you brothers and sisters are viewing pornography, stop it right now! Stop it absolutely! It is as destructive as leprosy, as addictive as meth, and as corrosive as lye.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p46">Carnal temptation is not new. The Apostle Peter warned of this same snare when he wrote:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p47">“They allure through the lusts of the flesh … those that were clean. …</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p48">“While they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption: for of whom a man is overcome, of the same is he brought in bondage.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="27"><a href="#27">27</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p49">Avoid that bondage, my beloved brothers and sisters. If you are presently viewing pornography, stop it! And stop it now! Seek help from your bishop. None are smart enough to outwit the adversary on their own once they have been poisoned by pornography.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p50">Now let me move to another serious question: <i>Will you choose to follow the Lord or the philosophies of men?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p51">For example, arguments swirl around that the earth is dangerously overpopulated and that couples should restrict the number of their children. Have you heard that one? However, at the fifth World Congress of Families, in 2009, Sister Nelson and I heard a scholar present a paper in which he made a stunning statement. He said that if each man, woman, and child now living upon the earth were allotted a quarter of an acre of land, all 6.8 billion people would fit in the country of Brazil, with 20 percent of Brazil still left unoccupied.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="28"><a href="#28">28</a></sup> Does that sound like the earth is overcrowded?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p52">I checked that calculation. It is correct. I adjure you to believe the Lord, who said that “the earth is full, and there is enough and to spare.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="29"><a href="#29">29</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p53">Another reality is that you live at a time when unemployment is high and financial markets throughout the world are jittery. Again, a worldly solution is to look at alternatives to God’s plan. But we know that strong marriages and families actually help the economy to thrive. And we are not alone in those feelings.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p54">The scholar Dr. Patrick F. Fagan<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="30"><a href="#30">30</a></sup> wrote: “The indispensable building block upon which the fortunes of the economy depends [is] the married-parent household—especially the child-rich family that worships weekly. …</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p55">“… Every marriage creates a new household, an independent economic unit that generates income, spends, saves, and invests.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="31"><a href="#31">31</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p56">Dr. Fagan added that “the married mother at home exerts a more far-reaching impact on the economy than [does] the married father in the workplace. … While the husband contributes to the present economy, the mother contributes to both present and future economy.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="32"><a href="#32">32</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p57">Dr. Fagan’s report confirms concepts expressed years ago by the First Presidency and the Twelve Apostles in “The Family: A Proclamation to the World.” I hope that each of you has a copy. Study it carefully. While the family is under attack across the entire world, the truths of the family proclamation will fortify you.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p58">You wonderful youth of the noble birthright, you need to understand the far-reaching consequences of society’s current skirmish over the very definition of marriage. The present debate involves the question of whether two people of the same gender can be married. If you have a question about the position of the Church on this or any other important issue, prayerfully ponder it, and then heed the prophetic messages at this forthcoming October general conference of the Church. Those inspired addresses, plus inspiration from the Holy Ghost, will bring to your mind a fuller and truer understanding.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p59">The marriage debate is but one of the many controversies that will challenge you in the future. Against the strident voices of the adversary, you, as youth of the noble birthright, will choose to stand for the Lord and His truth. Remember the words of the following hymn. Repeat them. Memorize them. This hymn is all about you:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.f1">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">Shall the youth of Zion falter</div>
                        <div class="line">In defending truth and right?</div>
                        <div class="line">While the enemy assaileth,</div>
                        <div class="line">Shall we shrink or shun the fight? No!</div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.f2">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">True to the faith that our parents have cherished,</div>
                        <div class="line">True to the truth for which martyrs have perished,</div>
                        <div class="line">To God’s command,</div>
                        <div class="line">Soul, heart, and hand,</div>
                        <div class="line">Faithful and true we will ever stand.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="33"><a href="#33">33</a></sup></div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p69">The Apostle Paul prophesied about the plight of our day. His description sounds like our 10:00 nightly news broadcast. Listen!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p70">“In the last days perilous times shall come.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p71">“For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p72">“Without natural affection, trucebreakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those that are good,</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p73">“Traitors, heady, highminded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God;</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p74">“Having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof: from such turn away.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="34"><a href="#34">34</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p75">That’s the end of his warning.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p76">Paul’s accurate vision of the spiritual devastation of our day was followed by his reassuring conclusion, telling us how to stay safe: “From a child thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="35"><a href="#35">35</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p77">To his advice I would add my own: Keep studying the scriptures. Keep doing the things that build your faith in Jesus Christ. And then notice the wise choices you are naturally drawn to make.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p78">Your faith in Jesus Christ and His gospel will give you the courage to marry and to bring children into your family while you are young and able to have them. When you are my age, you will prize your children, your grandchildren, and their children above any fame or fortune that otherwise might have come.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p79">Now for a question I pray that you will consider on a daily basis: <i>How will you prepare for your personal interview with the Savior?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p80">You youth of the noble birthright are not perfect yet. None of us are. So, you, along with the rest of us, are very grateful for the Atonement of the Savior, which provides full forgiveness as you truly repent. You also know that your stay here in mortality is relatively brief. (And the older you get, the more you realize that.) In time, each of you will graduate from this frail existence and move on to the next world.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p81">Judgment day awaits each one of us. I don’t know whether the heavenly gate is pearly or not, but I do know, as do all students of the Book of Mormon, that “the keeper of the gate is the Holy One of Israel; and he employ[s] no servant there; … for the Lord God is his name.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="36"><a href="#36">36</a></sup> Yes, each one of us will have a personal interview with Jesus Christ.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p82">Each day on earth gives you time and opportunity to prepare for that interview. Please know this: As you choose to live on the Lord’s side, you are never alone. God has given you access to His help while you move along through mortality’s perilous pathway. As you diligently, earnestly pour out your heart to Him in daily prayer, He will send His angels to help you.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="37"><a href="#37">37</a></sup> He has given you the Holy Ghost to be by your side as you live worthily. He has given you scriptures so that you can fully feast upon the words of Jesus Christ.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="38"><a href="#38">38</a></sup> He has given you words to heed from living prophets.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p83">He has given you an opportunity to receive a patriarchal blessing. It will provide insight about your connection to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob and the covenant made with them for their posterity. Your patriarchal blessing also provides insight about your potential in life here and hereafter. Each of these and other divine aids will help you to choose well so that you may look forward to your meeting, face to face, with our Lord and Savior.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p84">My last question: <i>In whom will you put your trust?</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p85">You youth of the noble birthright know that God is your Father. He loves you. He wants you to be happy. Put your trust in Him.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="39"><a href="#39">39</a></sup> Maintain your focus on His holy temple. Be worthy to receive your endowment and sealing ordinances. Remain faithful to those covenants, and return frequently to the temple. Remember, your loftiest goal is to gain the greatest of all the blessings of God, that of eternal life.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="40"><a href="#40">40</a></sup> Ordinances of the temple are essential for that blessing.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="41"><a href="#41">41</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p86">I invite you to study prayerfully the scriptural statement of your identity, purpose, and blessing, as recorded in section 86 of the Doctrine and Covenants. It is about you. Listen!</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p87">“Thus saith the Lord unto you [youth of the noble birthright], with whom the priesthood hath continued through the lineage of your fathers—</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p88">“For ye are lawful heirs, according to the flesh, and have been hid from the world with Christ in God—</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p89">“Therefore <i>your</i> life and the priesthood have remained, and must needs remain through <i>you</i> and your lineage until the restoration of all things spoken by the mouths of all the holy prophets since the world began.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p90">“Therefore, blessed are <i>ye</i> if ye continue in my goodness, a light unto the Gentiles, and through this priesthood, a savior unto my people Israel.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="42"><a href="#42">42</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p91">Yes, you truly are youth of the noble birthright, created in God’s image. You are the lawful heirs, to be tried and tested. You may choose to be a light to the world, to help save God’s children, to have joy, and ultimately to earn the blessing of eternal life.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p92">Now, to assist you in these critical choices before you, I would like to bestow a blessing upon you. Invoking the keys of the holy apostleship vested in me, I bless you that you may feast upon the words of Jesus Christ and apply His teachings into your lives. I bless you with the power to live as He would have you live and, through your example of righteousness, become worthy of emulation as a member of the Church that bears His holy name. I bless you with success in your educational and occupational pursuits, to the end that you can render service of worth to your fellow human beings. I bless you with health and strength needed to fulfill the divine destiny that God has in store for each of you, that His will may be done by you and through you.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p93">I so bless you and bear my testimony that God lives! Jesus is the Christ. This is His Church. He directs it through His prophets and apostles. We love and sustain Thomas S. Monson as President of the Lord’s Church today. This testimony and blessing I leave with you, my beloved brothers and sisters, with my sincere expression of love for each one of you, in the sacred name of Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.p94">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 1/13. testPD00048932 000</block>
            </div>
            <div class="notes">
                <div class="title">Notes</div>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn1" ref="1">
                    <p><span class="label">1.</span> See “Carry On,” <i>Hymns,</i> no. 255.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn2" ref="2">
                    <p><span class="label">2.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/acts/3.25" class="scriptureRef">Acts 3:25</a>; see also <a href="/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/15.18" class="scriptureRef">1 Nephi 15:18</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/20.25" class="scriptureRef">3 Nephi 20:25</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn3" ref="3">
                    <p><span class="label">3.</span> See “Hope of Israel,” <i>Hymns,</i> no. 259.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn4" ref="4">
                    <p><span class="label">4.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/13.2-3" class="scriptureRef">Alma 13:2–3</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn5" ref="5">
                    <p><span class="label">5.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/132.63" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 132:63</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn6" ref="6">
                    <p><span class="label">6.</span> “Know This, That Every Soul Is Free,” <i>Hymns,</i> no. 240.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn7" ref="7">
                    <p><span class="label">7.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/93.36" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 93:36</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn8" ref="8">
                    <p><span class="label">8.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/130.18-19" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 130:18–19</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn9" ref="9">
                    <p><span class="label">9.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-tim/4.12" class="scriptureRef">1 Timothy 4:12</a>; see also <a href="/scriptures/nt/heb/13.7" class="scriptureRef">Hebrews 13:7</a>. The Greek word <i>anastrophe,</i> from which <i>conversation</i> was translated, means an upward manner of living.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn10" ref="10">
                    <p><span class="label">10.</span> Ardeth Greene Kapp, <i>I Walk by Faith</i> (1987), 97.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn11" ref="11">
                    <p><span class="label">11.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/82.3" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 82:3</a>; see also <a href="/scriptures/nt/luke/12.48" class="scriptureRef">Luke 12:48</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn12" ref="12">
                    <p><span class="label">12.</span> See “We Are All Enlisted,” <i>Hymns,</i> no. 250.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn13" ref="13">
                    <p><span class="label">13.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/nt/rev/12.7-9" class="scriptureRef">Revelation 12:7–9</a>; <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/29.40-41" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 29:40–41</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn14" ref="14">
                    <p><span class="label">14.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/10.4" class="scriptureRef">1 Nephi 10:4</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn15" ref="15">
                    <p><span class="label">15.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/pgp/moses/4.3" class="scriptureRef">Moses 4:3</a>. Some people describe agency as “free agency.” But that expression is not scriptural. Scripture speaks only of <i>moral</i> agency (see <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/101.78" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 101:78</a>).</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn16" ref="16">
                    <p><span class="label">16.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/2.27" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 2:27</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn17" ref="17">
                    <p><span class="label">17.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/41.10" class="scriptureRef">Alma 41:10</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn18" ref="18">
                    <p><span class="label">18.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/10.23" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 10:23</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn19" ref="19">
                    <p><span class="label">19.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/john/17.3" class="scriptureRef">John 17:3</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn20" ref="20">
                    <p><span class="label">20.</span> Joseph Smith Translation, <a href="/scriptures/nt/matt/6.38" class="scriptureRef">Matthew 6:38</a> (in Matthew 6:33, footnote <i>a</i>).</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn21" ref="21">
                    <p><span class="label">21.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/14.7" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 14:7</a>; <a href="/scriptures/pgp/moses/1.39" class="scriptureRef">Moses 1:39</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn22" ref="22">
                    <p><span class="label">22.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/1.16" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 1:16</a>; <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/89.4" class="scriptureRef">89:4</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn23" ref="23">
                    <p><span class="label">23.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/nt/1-tim/6.5-6,11" class="scriptureRef">1 Timothy 6:5–6, 11</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn24" ref="24">
                    <p><span class="label">24.</span> See Boyd K. Packer, “Counsel to Youth,” <i>Ensign </i>or <i>Liahona,</i> Nov. 2011, 18.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn25" ref="25">
                    <p><span class="label">25.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/38.13" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 38:13</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn26" ref="26">
                    <p><span class="label">26.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/38.28" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 38:28</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn27" ref="27">
                    <p><span class="label">27.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/2-pet/2.18-19" class="scriptureRef">2 Peter 2:18–19</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn28" ref="28">
                    <p><span class="label">28.</span> See Don Feder, “The Perpetual-Crisis Machine of the Apocalyptic Left,” donfeder.com/articles/1002chickenLittle.htm.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn29" ref="29">
                    <p><span class="label">29.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/104.17" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 104:17</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn30" ref="30">
                    <p><span class="label">30.</span> Dr. Patrick F. Fagan is a senior fellow at the Family Research Council and directs the Marriage and Religion Research Institute in Washington, D.C.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn31" ref="31">
                    <p><span class="label">31.</span> Patrick F. Fagan, “The Family GDP: How Marriage and Fertility Drive the Economy,” <i>The Family in America,</i> vol. 24, no. 2, spring 2010, 136.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn32" ref="32">
                    <p><span class="label">32.</span> Patrick F. Fagan, “The Family GDP,” 142.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn33" ref="33">
                    <p><span class="label">33.</span> “True to the Faith,” <i>Hymns,</i> no. 254.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn34" ref="34">
                    <p><span class="label">34.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/2-tim/3.1-5" class="scriptureRef">2 Timothy 3:1–5</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn35" ref="35">
                    <p><span class="label">35.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/nt/2-tim/3.15" class="scriptureRef">2 Timothy 3:15</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn36" ref="36">
                    <p><span class="label">36.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/9.41" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 9:41</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn37" ref="37">
                    <p><span class="label">37.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/84.88" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 84:88</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn38" ref="38">
                    <p><span class="label">38.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/9.51" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 9:51</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/32.3" class="scriptureRef">32:3</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn39" ref="39">
                    <p><span class="label">39.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/4.34" class="scriptureRef">2 Nephi 4:34</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/28.31" class="scriptureRef">28:31</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn40" ref="40">
                    <p><span class="label">40.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/14.7" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 14:7</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn41" ref="41">
                    <p><span class="label">41.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/131.1-3" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 131:1–3</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/youth-of-the-noble-birthright-what-will-you-choose.fn42" ref="42">
                    <p><span class="label">42.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/86.8-11" class="scriptureRef">Doctrine and Covenants 86:8–11</a>; emphasis added.</p>
                </block>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
        <ldswebml type="article" xml:lang="eng" locale="eng" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him" status="publish" dup-conf="false" dup-mag="false" order="100.testPD00048935.011" toc="yes" xml:base="ces-devotionals/testPD00048935_000_11.xml">
            <search-meta>
                <title>I Will Give Myself to Him</title>
                <uri-title translate="no">i-will-give-myself-to-him</uri-title>
                <source translate="no">testPD00048935_000_11</source>
                <item-number>testPD00048935</item-number>
                <collections translate="no">
                    <collection>global-search</collection>
                    <collection>gospel-library</collection>
                    <collection>manuals</collection>
                </collections>
                <subjects>
                    <subject>Will</subject>
                </subjects>
                <publication-type translate="no">manual</publication-type>
                <publication-date value="2013-01-01" year="2013" month="01">2013</publication-date>
                <web-publish-date translate="no">2013-11-14T15:49:16.50442-07:00</web-publish-date>
                <authors>
                    <author uri="/church/leader/russell-t-osguthorpe">
                        <author-name>Russell T. Osguthorpe</author-name>
                        <author-title>Sunday School General President</author-title>
                        <author-role value="auxiliary-presidency" translate="no" living="1">Auxiliary Presidency</author-role>
                        <author-rank translate="no">10</author-rank>
                        <author-seniority translate="no">01</author-seniority>
                        <image type="jpg" uri="russell-t-osguthorpe-10.jpg" translate="no"/>
                    </author>
                </authors>
            </search-meta>
            <block type="heading" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.head11">
                <h1>I Will Give Myself to Him</h1>
                <div class="authorName">Russell T. Osguthorpe</div>
                <div class="authorRole">Sunday School General President</div>
                <div class="event">CES Devotional for Young Adults • November 3, 2013 • Brigham Young University</div>
            </block>
            <div class="bodyBlock">
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p5">It is such a privilege to be with you tonight, my dear young brothers and sisters. I want you to know what a blessing it is for my wife and me to be with you this evening. When we look at you, we see countless possibilities. You are so full of potential. No matter how high your hopes, I’m here to tell you they can be even higher. You can accomplish more in this life than you know. With the Lord at your side, you can experience miracles. You can do the thing that you first thought impossible. You can overcome any problem. You can rise above anything that would pull you down. You can reject evil and embrace everything that is good. You came to earth for a purpose, and with the Lord’s help you will achieve that purpose.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p6">I hope you realize how many are praying for you. There are so many prayers offered in this Church every day for the youth of the Church—for the young adults. Sometime, when you have a quiet moment, I invite you to reflect on all of the prayers that are offered every day specifically for you, the rising generation. Prayers in the temples, prayers by General Authorities and general officers of the Church, prayers by stake and ward leaders, and prayers by parents, other family members, and friends—I hear many of these prayers. They’re heartfelt. I hope you will reflect on the powers that are being drawn from the heavens in your behalf.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p7">And I hope you feel loved, not only by those who know you, but by all those who care for you and care about you even though they may never have met you. I know that if President Monson were here today, he would express his love to you. We have a living prophet who loves the youth of this Church.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p8">My wife and I are so grateful to this choir for singing the song “I Will Give Myself to Him.” We wrote the song for our missionaries while serving in the South Dakota Rapid City Mission, but the words apply to all of us throughout our lives. The first verse says:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.f1">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">He gave Himself for me, He died that I might live.</div>
                        <div class="line">What can I do for Him? What can I really give?<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="1"><a href="#1">1</a></sup></div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p11">These are the words of someone reflecting on the blessings of the Atonement, the blessings of feeling the love of our Father in Heaven and His Son, Jesus Christ. We all have moments like this—moments when we know the Lord is mindful of us.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p12">I invite you to reflect right now on the blessings that you feel as a member of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, and if there is someone in this audience who is considering joining the Church, I invite you to reflect on a blessing you are seeking. Then I would like you to share that blessing with the person sitting next to you. If you’re not acquainted with that person—even better—you can become acquainted as you share. Share as many blessings as you can in the next minute or two.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p13">I recently invited a group of students to my home to discuss the topic for this evening. Let’s see what they said when I asked them to share their feelings about blessings in their lives:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p14"> <span class="strong">Male 1:</span> The knowledge that I have—the knowledge of the plan of salvation, my Heavenly Father, and what He’s like and what He wants for me, and knowing what I can do to live my life in harmony with what He wants for me. Blessings that come from the sealing power and from temples on the earth—knowing that I can be with my family forever, as a family.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p15"> <span class="strong">Female 1:</span> The knowledge of the Atonement, and then the ability to gain access to the power that comes through the Atonement. A lot of it is through the ordinances of the priesthood and feeling a very real connection with my Heavenly Father through those ordinances and the covenants that I make with Him. To have power in our lives, to have strength and all the things that we need to get back to Him.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p16"> <span class="strong">Female 2:</span> The opportunity and privilege to have the gift of the Holy Ghost with us always, to guide our decisions in submitting our wills and to give us that comfort and strength and that power to make it through this life and then to be with Him forever afterwards.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p17"> <span class="strong">Male 2:</span> I feel like all of these are blessings of the priesthood that are available to both men and women. I’m really grateful for the priesthood that was restored so that we could have all of these blessings: the temple, the Holy Ghost, the opportunity to access the Atonement.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p18"> <span class="strong">Female 3:</span> How grateful I am to know I can progress and that this life is not about being apathetic or sitting on a fence—or sitting anywhere. It’s about standing up and going somewhere. And to me, progression is so essential to know that that happens and that it can still happen even beyond death.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p19"> <span class="strong">Male 3:</span> The Book of Mormon. As a student I spend so much time reading stuff that I have to have this guard—like, Is this true? What assumptions do they have?  How am I going to sift through all the stuff they’re saying? But I feel like I can just take off my shoes, so to speak, when I read the Book of Mormon. Because it’s just true—translated by the gift and power of God.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p20">Without the restored gospel of Jesus Christ, we would have none of the blessings my friends just mentioned. Reflecting on our blessings gives us strength to move forward in life, but we all know that moving forward is challenging. This is mortality, and mortality is not easy. The second two verses of the song the choir sang say:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.f2">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">When others turn away, when no one seems to care,</div>
                        <div class="line">How can I feel His love? How will I know He’s there?</div>
                        <div class="line">. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</div>
                        <div class="line">When pain and sadness come to those who question why,</div>
                        <div class="line">How will I bring them peace? How will I help them try?<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="2"><a href="#2">2</a></sup></div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p26">This time I invite you to write down—or simply make a mental note—of challenges that you are facing right now in your life, concerns that sometimes keep you awake at night.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p27">I asked my friends who came to my home what their challenges were, and this is what they said:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p28"> <span class="strong">Female 2:</span> Lots of thoughts right off the bat! One thing I was thinking is that it’s easy to tie your worth and your identity with accomplishments: I haven’t gotten married yet, or I haven’t gotten a bachelor’s degree or a master’s degree yet, or those things you do or don’t accomplish.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p29"> <span class="strong">Male 2:</span> Maintaining the spirituality that we had while we were serving full-time for the Lord. That’s something that I have to choose daily, whether I will be able to continue the same habits that I developed on the mission or not.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p30"> <span class="strong">Male 1:</span> One of the biggest things that brought the Spirit into our lives during the mission was our opportunity to minister and to bear testimony that continues through home and visiting teaching and through fellowshipping—with great opportunities to do many meaningful things. And that same Spirit can be with us as we minister to others.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p31"> <span class="strong">Male 3:</span> Finding the right balance between being guided by the Spirit and inspiration in the decisions you make in your life and just making them. Some people just seem like they have a lot of guidance from the Lord. And some people just have to work on things and just go for it before they know what’s right or not.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p32"> <span class="strong">Female 1:</span> An overarching theme, like delayed blessings and understanding that they will come at some point. But just having that faith and trust and submitting our will to Heavenly Father.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p33"> <span class="strong">Female 3:</span> Why do bad things happen to good people? Or hard things—really, really difficult things—happen to good people? That has been something that has been on my mind. For example, I just found out my dad has cancer. And I thought, “How does that happen to a man who has served so much?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p34">Whatever your challenge, I testify that the topic we will discuss this evening can help you overcome it.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p35">To begin, let’s reflect for a moment on our last CES devotional. In the apostolic blessing that Elder Russell M. Nelson pronounced on that occasion, he said, “I bless you … that [God’s] will may be done by you and through you.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="3"><a href="#3">3</a></sup> Consider the power of these words. If God’s will is to be done by us and through us, then our will needs to be the same as God’s. We need to want what He wants.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p36">Elder Neal A. Maxwell once said: “As you submit your wills to God, you are giving Him the <i>only</i> thing you <i>can</i> actually give Him that is really yours to give. Don’t wait too long to find the altar or to begin to place the gift of your wills upon it!”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="4"><a href="#4">4</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p37">This evening I invite you to consider with me three questions: (1) What is the meaning of the word <i>will?</i> (2) How do we give our will to God? and (3) How can we know that we’re succeeding?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p38">First, what does the word <i>will</i> mean? We don’t often talk about will, at least using that word. Sometimes we say “willpower.” For example, “I just don’t have the willpower to resist that cheesecake.” So will is the “inclination <i>to do</i> something,”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="5"><a href="#5">5</a></sup> the desire that causes us to act.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p39">If you ask people in the United States to name the two most important things for our physical health, nearly 95 percent say “diet and exercise”—like we would think. Then, if you ask these same people, “Are you eating right and exercising enough?”—what do you think they would say? Between 5 percent and 10 percent say they are. There is an obvious gap between knowing something and doing it. Most people know what they should do, but few have the will to do it.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p40">An example from our mission shows that when we get help we can develop the will to do what we know we should do.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p41">One of our assistants on our mission once said to his companion, “Hey, I’ve gained 30 pounds since I came on a mission. I can’t go home like this. Could you help me lose some weight?” (He was on a basketball team, and he didn’t want to go back like that.)</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p42">His companion agreed.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p43">Soon after that I was following these two missionaries in a buffet line. The missionary who wanted to lose weight went to pick up a brownie. His companion whispered in his ear, “You don’t want that.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p44">The hungry missionary, a little put out, said, “Oh, yeah, I do want that.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p45">“No, you don’t want that; you really don’t,” counseled his companion.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p46">The missionary did not take the brownie.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p47">This missionary wanted to lose weight, but he needed help overcoming his desire for that brownie. Remember that line in the song that said, “How will I help them try?” The companion was helping his fellow missionary try to do what he really wanted to do but could not do without a little outside help from someone else. He was trying to help this missionary see that his desire to be healthy could overcome his desire for that brownie. He was trying to help him strengthen his will.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p48">The adversary would have us believe that there is no such thing as will—that we have no choice but to follow our own natural impulses—to eat as many brownies as we can. Some mistakenly believe that our will is predetermined by our genes and that we have no control at all over it.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p49">To show how pivotal a question this is, I share an excerpt from a recent news article. The author is a respected professor of biology. Here’s how he begins his essay entitled “Why You Don’t Really Have Free Will.” This title caught my eye because, as a member of the Church, I know that we <i>do</i> have will.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p50">He explains that the decisions we think we make, we don’t really make at all. Speaking of the choices we made for breakfast this morning, he says: “You may <i>feel</i> like you’ve made choices, but in reality your decision … to have eggs or pancakes [this morning] was determined long before you were aware of it—perhaps even before you woke up today. And your ‘will’ had no part in that decision.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="6"><a href="#6">6</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p51">So, he is saying that we have no will, no control over our desires. We are simply subject to whatever our genes dictate. When I read this article, I wanted to tell him about our missionary. He actually did make choices. He did lose his 30 pounds. His <i>will</i> overcame his bodily desires.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p52">We learn from revelation, both ancient and modern, that we do have agency, that we do have will, that we do have desires, and that those desires can change. Elder Russell M. Nelson, in the most recent general conference, said: “We can change our behavior. Our very desires can change. How? … Permanent change … can come only through the healing, cleansing, and enabling power of the Atonement of Jesus Christ.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="7"><a href="#7">7</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p53">When Elder Maxwell said that our will is the only thing we can really give to God, he was teaching that anything else we give is something that God already gave to us. When we give tithes or offerings, we are simply giving back to God what He first gave to us. Any money we earn in this life, for example, comes to us because of God’s creations. If we give our time, we are giving what God already gave to us—our days upon the earth. But when we give our will to Him, this is a gift that is uniquely ours to give. When we give our will, we are giving ourselves totally, withholding nothing.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p54">Here’s what my friends said when I asked them to search the scriptures and then give their thoughts about the meaning of the word <i>will:</i></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p55"> <span class="strong">Male 3:</span> Being “willing to submit to all things which the Lord seeth fit to inflict upon [them], even as a child doth submit to his father.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="8"><a href="#8">8</a></sup> So that’s talking about yielding and submitting and being willing. Then we kind of got talking about it, and it led us to this other scripture in <a href="/scriptures/bofm/hel/3" class="scriptureRef">Helaman 3</a>.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p56"> <span class="strong">Male 1:</span> <a href="/scriptures/bofm/hel/3.35" class="scriptureRef">Helaman 3:35</a>—“Yea, even to the purifying and the sanctification of their hearts, which sanctification cometh because of their yielding their hearts unto God.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p57"> <span class="strong">Female 3:</span> This doesn’t happen all at once, I don’t think, but it’s definitely a process that comes with time and work.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p58"> <span class="strong">Male 2:</span> I feel almost like you gain momentum. As you make the right choice, it’s easier to make the right choice the next time. Prayer and daily scripture study and pondering and writing in a journal.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p59"> <span class="strong">Female 2:</span> In <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/5.2" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 5:2</a>, it talks about how they describe the mighty change within us and in our hearts that we had “no more disposition to do evil, but to do good continually.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p60"> <span class="strong"> Female 1:</span> It’s funny because we were reading the exact same scriptures, but we were having a totally different conversation. I really did think that was super powerful in <a href="/scriptures/bofm/hel/3.35" class="scriptureRef">Helaman 3:35</a>, about yielding our hearts unto God and how that sanctifies us. I think it involves a lot of trust to yield to Him and say, “No, I’m going to trust right now that your plan is perfect. I’m going to give you my will and allow you to then use that to mold me and become who you need me to be.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p61"> <span class="strong">Male 2:</span> We were talking about the War in Heaven—how we fought for agency and how we decided to follow Christ and do what He would have us do. We talked about how in this life it’s almost a battle of wills: Will we decide to desire what Christ would want, to become like He is, rather than just saying that we will do the things that He asks us to—will we want to do them?</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p62">So, giving our will to the Lord does not mean that we give up our agency. In reality, the opposite is true. The more we give our will to the Lord, the more our own ability to exercise our moral agency grows. Knowing what God wants us to know, saying what He wants us to say, doing what He wants us to do all lead us to being what He wants us to be. God gave us agency so we could yield ourselves to Him, not so we could succumb to temptation.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p63">When you look inside and dig down deep, you can find the desires that lead to your most prized actions. You’ll notice that I did not say “that lead to any actions”—because some of our actions are not motivated by our deepest, most strongly held desires. Some actions happen with little thought. Some actions even seem to go completely against what we most deeply desire.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p64">A young man once came to me for help in the repentance process. While describing the sorrow he felt for what he had done, he said, “Looking back on it, I can’t believe I actually did it. It’s like somebody else did it and not me.” Deep in his heart he did not want to do what he had done, but somehow the natural man took over, and he yielded to the enticings of the adversary rather than to the enticings of the Holy Ghost, who would have helped him resist temptation.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="9"><a href="#9">9</a></sup> He was talking about will. He wanted to be good, but there was some part of him—some aspect of his own will—that he had not yet yielded. He was withholding that little part, and that’s what led him to do something he regretted. But he came to a priesthood leader to make things right—to be who he really was, a faithful son of his Father in Heaven. He came so he could try to yield all of his will to the Lord, this time withholding nothing.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p65">This young man experienced a change of heart. He had “no more [desire] to do evil, but to do good continually.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="10"><a href="#10">10</a></sup> His desires had changed, and because his desires had changed, his conduct also changed. He was putting off the natural man and yielding to the enticings of the Holy Spirit. A change of heart is a change of motive, not only a change in action. We need to do good things, but even more, we need to do them for the right reason.</block>
                <img src="/bc/content/ldsorg/broadcasts/CES/November 2013/CES131114_sab001_inl.jpg" alt="Motives and Actions Diagram" target-url="/bc/content/ldsorg/broadcasts/CES/November 2013/CES131114_sab001.pdf"/>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p67">This diagram helps me understand the relationship between our motives or desires and our actions. When we’re on the covenant path of discipleship, our motives are pure and our actions are righteous. We do good things because we love the Lord and His children. But it is also possible to do a good thing with an unrighteous motive. Then we are acting as the hypocrites—we do good because we want to look good, or because we want to look better than somebody else.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p68">If we do an unrighteous act with an unrighteous motive, we are, as the scriptures say, “willfully [rebelling] against God.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="11"><a href="#11">11</a></sup> Those in this frame are proud of the bad things they do. But when we really want to be good but slip and fall, we are yielding to the natural man or woman within us. When we find ourselves anywhere other than on the path of discipleship, we need to draw upon the powers of the Atonement by repenting, and we will once again be on the right path.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p69">This repentance process is clearly a process of changing desires. It is a process of making space for the Spirit. And when we make space for the Spirit, there is no space left for sin.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p70">So, our will is the collective force of our desires or motives. Our will underlies our actions. How do we go about strengthening our will? How can we give our will to the Lord? I invite the choir to sing again the chorus of the song they sang at the opening of our devotional this evening. Listen carefully to the words:</block>
                <block type="figure" sub-type="poetry" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.f3">
                    <div class="stanza">
                        <div class="line">I will say what He wants said. I will do what He wants done.</div>
                        <div class="line">I will be a witness to the world of God’s Beloved Son.</div>
                        <div class="line">I will give myself to Him—my heart, my will, my soul.</div>
                        <div class="line">I will always sing redeeming love, the song that makes me whole.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="12"><a href="#12">12</a></sup></div>
                    </div>
                </block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p75">We can all say what He wants said.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p76">While serving as a stake president, I interviewed a sister who had recently married. I asked, “How is your marriage going?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p77">She responded, “Well, it’s okay, I think. We don’t fight very much.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p78">I asked, “What do you mean, very much?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p79">She said, “Well, you know, all married couples fight.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p80">I responded, “Not all married couples. My wife and I don’t fight. My parents didn’t fight.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p81">We then had a great conversation about how she and her husband could talk to each other in love rather than in frustration or harshness.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p82">We can say what the Lord would have us say. We can eliminate harshness from our words and our tone. We can lift and build others rather than tearing them down.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p83">I once accompanied Elder Jeffrey R. Holland to reorganize a stake presidency. When we entered the hotel where we were staying, he recognized a hotel clerk and asked her, “So, how’s that nice boyfriend of yours?”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p84">She said, “Oh, we broke up just a few weeks ago.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p85">He said, “Well, you’ll find another one, and he’ll be even better.”</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p86">She smiled, and we went on. The next day I watched as Elder Holland complimented members and leaders, one after another. He did it with ease in such natural ways that everyone we met felt better about themselves and about life—just because he built them up.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p87">We can all do this. If the Savior were here, He would uplift everyone in His path, just as He did when He was here upon the earth. We can all say what He wants said.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p88">When someone asks me what it is like serving with General Authorities, the first thing that comes to my mind is the love that I feel when I’m around them. One might think that standing at the podium in the Conference Center is impossibly intimidating because the First Presidency and Quorum of the Twelve are sitting right behind you as you speak. But they somehow give you the feeling you can actually do it.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p89">As soon as you’ve finished speaking, the Twelve extend their hand and thank you for your contribution to the meeting as you make your way back to your seat. The first time this happened, I was a little taken aback. I was not expecting them to be quite so expressive, but they are. They build everyone in their path, just as the Savior did. This is really the hallmark of President Monson.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p90">President Monson shows love to everyone. Following one of the sessions at October conference, President Monson saw a young boy waving to him. He bent over the rail and motioned for the boy to come closer. And then he shook his hand. The boy was understandably very excited.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p91">On another occasion, following a performance in the Conference Center, President Monson stayed after the meeting to shake hands with as many youth as possible. He walked onto the stage and approached a group of young people with severe disabilities. Even though these youth could not respond verbally to President Monson, the smiles on their faces showed how much they appreciated his handshake and hearty greeting.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p92">If we are reaching out to others, then our capacity to reach out increases even more. This is one of the clearest indicators that we are giving our will to God.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p93">So, we can say what the Lord wants us to say. We can also do what He wants done. Sometimes actions matter more than words.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p94">When we were raising our family, my wife got a serious infection and had to be hospitalized. I was trying to put food on the table and take care of our five young children while she was recuperating. But I didn’t have to work very hard to put food on the table. Meals were delivered to our door one after another—so many, in fact, that we couldn’t eat them all. So, I began putting these meals in the freezer until it was full.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p95">These actions might seem small in comparison to some acts of compassionate service, but I will tell you that those meals meant a lot. They rescued me. My wife was weak, and I was discouraged. But I could just go to the freezer to see what was for dinner that evening. With every meal those good ward members delivered to our doorstep, they were giving their will to God. They were doing what He wanted done.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p96">Those ward members had pure motives to help a family in need, but it’s possible to do a good thing with an improper motive. Then, as the scriptures teach, the good thing we do is actually counted as evil because our heart was not right.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="13"><a href="#13">13</a></sup> We did the good deed, but we did it reluctantly. So, desires are everything. We need to want what God wants. We need to say what He wants said because we <i>want</i> to say what He wants said. We need to do what He wants done because we <i>want</i> to do what He wants done. And we need to be a witness of God’s Beloved Son because we <i>want</i> to be a witness. Then we know we are giving our whole soul to Him—no little piece of us wants to do something contrary to His will.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p97">Saying and doing the right things become easier as we make promises to the Lord.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p98">Covenants play a central role in the development of will. When we are baptized, we covenant to take the Lord’s name upon us—to do what He would have us do. Then, every Sabbath day we renew that covenant. We witness to our Heavenly Father anew that we are still willing to take the Lord’s name upon us and remember Him and keep His commandments. Each time we worthily take that piece of sacramental bread in our hand or press that cup of water to our lips, we are giving our will to Him. We are saying, “I will be a witness to the world of God’s Beloved Son.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="14"><a href="#14">14</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p99">When we are sealed in the temple to our eternal mate, we again make covenants that strengthen our will. We can feel the strengthening power of the Atonement every time we enter God’s holy house. It is there that we covenant to consecrate ourselves to the Lord. This is why Elder Maxwell said, “Don’t wait too long to find the altar [and] to place the gift of your wills upon it.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="15"><a href="#15">15</a></sup> He may have been speaking metaphorically, but he was, I believe, also speaking clearly about how we can give our will to God by making and keeping covenants with Him.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p100">So, we do all we can to give ourselves to Him—our heart, our will, our soul. The more we follow this path, the more the Lord will bless us with His love. And the more we feel His love, the more we know we are succeeding in giving our will to Him.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p101">I hope we are learning something this evening that will help us fulfill Elder Nelson’s blessing—that God’s will can be done by us and through us. When I asked my friends what they had learned, this is what they said:</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p102"> <span class="strong">Male 2:</span> I think I’ve often coupled agency and giving my will to God, and this has helped me see them as two different things. I feel like I do a lot of the right things, but now that makes me want to go and purify the motive so that I can become what He wants me to become.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p103"> <span class="strong">Female 2:</span> I love making connections. I’m thinking, okay, this is what’s happening in my life, and oh, this is what I’ve been studying, and oh, this person said that. And, so, I guess I’ve just been making a lot of connections.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p104"> <span class="strong">Male 1:</span> No matter what our challenges, we just need to give more of ourselves to God. It’s like President Eyring says: “Hard as things seem today, they will be better in the next day if [we] choose to serve [God] this day.”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="16"><a href="#16">16</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p105"> <span class="strong">Male 3:</span> Giving your heart and your will to God … the first thing He does with it is He sanctifies it. It’s not like we’re all just giving our hearts to God and He just puts them in a big vault and says, “Yes, one more heart for me to enjoy.” He takes it and sanctifies it and proves it and gives it back to us and says, “Now go use this and do great things.” I just never really thought about what happened after you gave it to Him. I thought that was kind of the end, but that’s just the beginning.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p106"> <span class="strong">Female 3:</span> I know I don’t know everything, and it seems like the more I learn, the more I realize how much I don’t know. But I do know that God lives. And I think today was just more of a confirmation of that—that He is aware and He really is anxious and waiting and wants to bless His kids, and that’s us.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p107"> <span class="strong">Female 1:</span> About three days ago I got a priesthood blessing for something coming up in my life. And something said in the blessing was how I needed to have more trust in God and submit my will. But for some reason, during that blessing I felt very specifically that I needed to go and study that and what does that mean more deeply. How does that change the things I do every day and all day long and how to submit myself fully to Him.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p108">So, giving our will to the Lord is something we do every day. It is not an isolated act. It is not the end, but just the beginning. We can say what He wants said. We can do what He wants done. We can be a witness to the world of God’s Beloved Son—all because we <i>want</i> to do these things. When this change happens in our heart, our gratitude for the Atonement increases so much that we are strengthened by it continually.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p109">Alma said, “If ye have felt to sing the song of redeeming love, I would ask, can ye feel so now?”<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="17"><a href="#17">17</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p110">The song of redeeming love is a song of rejoicing in the Atonement of Jesus Christ. It is not necessarily a song with notes and lyrics; it is a song of feelings. The words we might use to express our gratitude when we want to sing the song of redeeming love are constantly changing, depending upon the specific blessings we receive. But this feeling of gratitude for the Savior is like a song. It can play itself over and over again in our heart every time we think about how the Redeemer has saved us from everything that would pull us down.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p111">That is why Alma asked if we felt like singing it now. Now is the moment that matters. If we feel like rejoicing in the Atonement of Jesus Christ right now, then our heart is right. We are giving our will to Him, and He is strengthening our will. If we are attracted to the things of the world, our heart is not right, and our will is not being strengthened.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p112">In the latter part of the Book of Mormon, the Nephites, who had once been a righteous people, turned away from the Lord. They began to boast in their own strength rather than rejoicing in the strength of the Lord. They <i>willfully</i> rebelled against God. And what happened to them? They were left to their own strength—to the point that they lost everything.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="18"><a href="#18">18</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p113">We don’t want to do that. We know we cannot make it on our own in this life. We just can’t do it. We need the Lord’s help. We need the help of each other. We simply can never rely on our own strength alone. The Lord’s outstretched arms invite us to be strengthened by Him so that we are never left to our own strength alone.<sup class="noteMarker" noteRef="19"><a href="#19">19</a></sup></block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p114">I know that we can accept His invitation to come and be strengthened, to come and be forgiven, to come and feel His infinite love. Then, with a smiling heart, we will want to sing the song of redeeming love. Not just once in a while—we will want to sing this song always. When we feel strength to do something difficult, we will sing the song in our heart. When we allow truth to find us and enlarge our soul, we will sing the song. When we feel forgiven, we will sing the song. And when we feel His love, we will sing the song.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p115">Each time we sing it, we will be giving our will to Him, the only gift we have to give Him. He will not only accept this gift, He will expand it and deepen it. He will cause us to feel more capable. He will help increase our capacity to love and be loved. He will lead us out of darkness into light. He will heal and help us in ways that permit us to forgive and be forgiven.</block>
                <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p116">I testify that He is our Savior and Redeemer. I testify that His Father loved us enough to send Him to earth to live and die for us. I know that this is His Church. I know that His living prophet, President Thomas S. Monson, understands the needs of the membership of the Church and knows how to help us find our way back home. In the name of Jesus Christ, amen.</block>
            </div>
            <div class="notes">
                <div class="title">Notes</div>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn1" ref="1">
                    <p><span class="label">1.</span> Russell T. Osguthorpe and Lola Osguthorpe, arr. Steve Schank, “I Will Give Myself to Him” (2009).</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn2" ref="2">
                    <p><span class="label">2.</span> Russell T. Osguthorpe and Lola Osguthorpe, “I Will Give Myself to Him.”</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn3" ref="3">
                    <p><span class="label">3.</span> Russell M. Nelson, “Youth of the Noble Birthright: What Will You Choose?” (Church Educational System devotional, Sept. 6, 2013); LDS.org.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn4" ref="4">
                    <p><span class="label">4.</span> Neal A. Maxwell, “Remember How Merciful the Lord Hath Been,” <i>Ensign</i> or<i> Liahona,</i> May 2004, 46.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn5" ref="5">
                    <p><span class="label">5.</span>  <i>Oxford English Dictionary,</i> “will”; oed.com.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn6" ref="6">
                    <p><span class="label">6.</span> Jerry A. Coyne, “Why You Don’t Really Have Free Will, USA Today, Jan. 1, 2012; usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/opinion/forum/story/2012–01–01/free-will-science-religion/52317624/1.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn7" ref="7">
                    <p><span class="label">7.</span> Russell M. Nelson, “Decisions for Eternity,” <i>Ensign</i> or<i> Liahona,</i> Nov. 2013, 108.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn8" ref="8">
                    <p><span class="label">8.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/3.19" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 3:19</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn9" ref="9">
                    <p><span class="label">9.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/3.19" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 3:19</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn10" ref="10">
                    <p><span class="label">10.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/5.2" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 5:2</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn11" ref="11">
                    <p><span class="label">11.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/mosiah/15.26" class="scriptureRef">Mosiah 15:26</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn12" ref="12">
                    <p><span class="label">12.</span> Russell T. Osguthorpe and Lola Osguthorpe, “I Will Give Myself to Him.”</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn13" ref="13">
                    <p><span class="label">13.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/moro/7.9" class="scriptureRef">Moroni 7:9</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn14" ref="14">
                    <p><span class="label">14.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/moro/4.3" class="scriptureRef">Moroni 4:3</a>; <a href="/scriptures/bofm/moro/5.2" class="scriptureRef">5:2</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn15" ref="15">
                    <p><span class="label">15.</span> Neal A. Maxwell, “Remember How Merciful the Lord Hath Been,” 46.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn16" ref="16">
                    <p><span class="label">16.</span> Henry B. Eyring, “This Day,” <i>Ensign</i> or<i> Liahona,</i> May 2007, 91.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn17" ref="17">
                    <p><span class="label">17.</span>  <a href="/scriptures/bofm/alma/5.26" class="scriptureRef">Alma 5:26</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn18" ref="18">
                    <p><span class="label">18.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/bofm/hel/4.13" class="scriptureRef">Helaman 4:13</a>.</p>
                </block>
                <block type="footnote" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.fn19" ref="19">
                    <p><span class="label">19.</span> See <a href="/scriptures/nt/matt/11.28" class="scriptureRef">Matthew 11:28</a>.</p>
                </block>
            </div>
            <div class="resources">
                <div class="copyrightInfo">
                    <block type="para" uri="/automation/transform/broadcasts/article/ces-devotionals/2018/01/i-will-give-myself-to-him.p137">© 2013 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. English approval: 1/13. Language. testPD00048935 000</block>
                </div>
            </div>
        </ldswebml>
    </div>
</ldswebml>